Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Needless to say, But check, she was a bad babe nevertheless. Callin' it quits now, baby, I'm alright.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Crash at my place, baby, alright?
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: This is sad.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: She was a bad nap.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Calling it quits now, baby, I'm a wreck. Crashed at my place, baby, you're a wreck. Diggin' in a bad way, losing your grip.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I don't know how that felt. Looking at you sideways, party on tilt. Certain things you just can't refuse She wanna ride me like a cruise, and I'm not trying to lose.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Unless I stuck by.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: You wanna sunflower?
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I think your love will be too much Or you'd be left… Unless I stuck by!
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Let the sun fly!
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: You're the sunflower Every time I'm leaving on you, you don't make it easy
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Wish I could be there for you. Give me reason to. Every time I walk in now, I can hear you telling me to turn around
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: You don't wanna be alone I know I always come and go.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: But it's out of my control And you'll be left in the dust Unless I start crying up.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: You're the sunflower I think your love would be too much Are you feeling?
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Dust Unless I stuck by ya.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: You're a sunflower A sunflower
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: What's poppin'? Brand new whip, just hopped in. I got options. I can pass that bitch like Stockton. Just jothing. I'ma spend this holiday locked in. My body got rid of them toxins. Sports in the top 10. I can put the ball in the end zone, put a bad bitch in the friend zone.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: This shit sound like an intro jet song, give me that tempo. Told pool, he'll fool with the shit. Told her, don't let her friends know. In the building, I move like a dime. Eating fettuccine or Vincenzos.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Me and my amigos got that free smoke on the West Coast, yeah, I'm talking about pre-rolls. Dark-haired bitches, she look like she go. She do. Hometown hero, feeling myself, can't murder my ego. She heard it my deep stroke, she said, babe, does it hurt when I deep throw? Certified freako, hangin' around dust, and she learning my lingo. Back then, wasn't worried about me, though. In the gym, tryna work on my free throw. Goddamn. Spending money at the club like Sam's.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Yes, ma'am. She a little freak on camera. But she don't put diss on the ground. Lil boys tryin' this on the ground. Hey, I can't switch on the fan. Shit's high, hit the switch on the fan.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: This where my head is. I feel resentment from every direction. Even some homies be wearing expressions. I be discouraged from sharing my blessings. We used to share a connection. Now it just feels like it's wearing and stretching. I'm getting real sick of taking advice from people that never could stare at reflections. Somewhere in there is a lesson. Y'all ain't evolving, it's very depressing. I'm at the club with the basketball team. Me and the Cardinals are sharing a section. Gotta cherish the present. I'm drinking water and wearing protection.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Got a career, and I'm very invested. Some people call it a scary obsession.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I like to call it a passion. I can be sitting, relaxin'. PG, we gettin' some traction. I'm at the venue, it's packed. I'm diggin' her accent. I got a B.B. Simon belt on me, and she trying to get it, I'm fastin'.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: That's my type of distraction, that's my type of shelatin'. Got my own flow, and I'm about to get a patent. Brand new sheets for the bed they sat in. Y'all wasn't tuned in back then. My swag day keep jacking. I ain't doing no verse, quit asking.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: What's poppin'? Brand new whip, just hopped in. I got options. I can pass that bitch like Stockton. Just jotting. I'm spending this holiday locked in. My body got rid of them toxins. Exploys in the top 10.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Buzzin' all the bells out the box, I just hit a link with the
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Headed with steak in a box.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Pour up the whole damn seal, I'ma get lazy. I got the mojo deals we been trippin'
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: She's sudden nigga, so… gotta cash out. Oh, don't wipe a nigga, no.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I won't never sell my soul, and I can beg that And I really wanna know when you wear wet.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Where the stash at? Crew the city in a bulletproof Cadillac.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Cause I know they niggas out there where the bag at. Gotta move smarter, gotta move harder. Nigga try to get me fire my water. I lay his ass down on my son or my daughter. I had the Draco with me, Dwayne Carter. Lotta niggas out here playing ain't ballin'. I done, put my whole arm in the rim, bins, cop you, and I know Papa get a key for the quarter.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Got a bitch that's lookin' like Aaliyah, she a model.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I'm about to get the key to the city.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Forgetting I had to cope at the lot. Turn the fuck 12 for a swat, bustin' all the bells out the box. I just hit a link with the box, had to put the stick in the box.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Pull up the whole damn seal, I'ma get lazy. I got the mojo deals we been trippin'
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: So don't wipe a nigga, no.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I won't never sell my soul, and I can beg that, and I really wanna know when you wear, where
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I've been movin' him out. They steal it with me, then he got the blues and the pops. Took her to the forest, put the wood in the mouth.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Bitch don't wear no shoes in my house. The pilot I'm flyin' in, I never wanna fly again. I take my chances in traffic. She's suckin' no dick, no hands with it. I just made a rolly plane like I
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I'm a 2020 president candidate. I done put a hundred bands on Zimmerman's shit. I've been moving real games, so that's why she pick a crit.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: My shit, got it out the mud. There's nothing you can tell me.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Yeah, when I had it South Street Wealthy.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: You ain't had to coop at the lot, told him for the 12 for a swap, bustin' all the bells out the box.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I just hit a leaf with the box, had to put the stick in the box.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Pour up the whole damn seal, I'ma get lazy. I got the mojo deals, we be traveling
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Don't wipe a nigga, no. Don't say slash
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I won't never sell my soul, and I can beg that And I really wanna know when you wear wet
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I put the new 4Gs on the G. I came into the bloody bottoms, it's underneath, cause all my niggas guy.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I keep a hundred racks since I… my jeans. I remember hitting them all with a whole team. Now, nigga, K, that's a cause, cause I'm bawling. I was waking up getting rags in the morning. I was broke, now I'm rich, these niggas salty.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: If I got up on a lien, I'ma sip sip. I run a wrestle with my queen like London and Nip.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: I got rich on all these niggas, I didn't forget back. I had to go through the struggle, I didn't forget that. I heard inside of the Maybach, and now I can sit back. These bitches know me now, cause I got them big rats, cause I'm gettin' money now.
Audio shared by 100xEngineers: Young nigga on the corner, bitch, I had to serve crack. Uncle frontin' me some peace, had to get him birds back. We came up on dirty money, I gave it a bird back. Cut off the rain and I gave my bitch a new poop. Either you runnin' y'all gang or your super woo. Got a New Orleans bitch in me, that pussy woo-doo. And I'm that nigga now.
100xEngineers: Hello, hello, good evening, good afternoon, good morning. How are you guys doing?
100xEngineers: Hi, Shefari. Hi, everyone.
100xEngineers: dissection.
100xEngineers: Awesome, let's do a quick wife check before we start.
100xEngineers: How are you guys feeling? On a scale of 1 to 10? Let me also see if you guys can chat. I think you guys can chat right now.
100xEngineers: Awesome.
100xEngineers: Chintan is at 8, Sacham is at 7, Poem is at 7.
100xEngineers: 9.6, very specific.
100xEngineers: Oh, awesome. Thank you so much, Abhishek, for that.
100xEngineers: Cool, I hope, like, the VIP score will increase as we progress through the lecture. This is one of the…
100xEngineers: turning point in our journey, by the way, this lecture and this week as well. I'll be sharing a lot of content. I hope all of you had
100xEngineers: Interesting time in the last couple of sessions, we…
100xEngineers: we started the journey from the idea, and I think this is… this is something which is very unique, right? Whenever I see, like.
100xEngineers: a new batch, going from idea to app, idea to discovery, it's always, like,
100xEngineers: Yeah, very hard to describe this feeling. It always feels like we are doing it first time. It just creates a childlike curiosity inside you, and I think I crave for those movements and those things in my life which actually makes
100xEngineers: me feel like a child again, because that's where I can, like, get into the flow state, and I can just, like, enjoy the creativity. I think one of those things is
100xEngineers: is this journey, like, and I hope, like, you guys are able to, like, use some of those things, maybe, your…
100xEngineers: first observation in this cohort, first idea, and hopefully now it is kind of making some shape. So, can we have a quick raise of hand before we continue the session? How many of you were able to form your own hypothesis? How many of you were able to form a hypotheses based on the observation you had?
100xEngineers: Tomorrow is, actually, today or tomorrow, maybe, I think I'm…
100xEngineers: Today is the last day for your submission, for assignment one.
100xEngineers: So deadline is reaching soon. How many of you, can we have a quick raise of hands?
100xEngineers: Gone from observation to hypothesis.
100xEngineers: Well… Creativity, yes.
100xEngineers: Very interesting. So we do have a lot of people who are following this, right? And I guess this is also, like, one of those kind of journeys which hopefully you will reflect back, and some people
100xEngineers: I spoke to, like, a couple of people here, and I know, like, you guys… you guys must be overwhelmed, you guys must be tired, you guys must be confused, some of you have a lot of things on your plate to do, and some of you are, like, still…
100xEngineers: figuring out the idea maze, okay, what should I build, and what should I pick? I have so many ideas, I have so many observations to do. But I think this entire phase, when you'll reflect back after a 6-month journey, and this happens, like, every time when we do this program, is that
100xEngineers: after 6 months, you'll reflect back that this is where you started. So, yeah, I think you guys should enjoy this moment a lot. One thing which I didn't do, and I would share, is
100xEngineers: Again, not to make this link dramatic, but…
100xEngineers: It's very tempting to go and build solutions right now.
100xEngineers: for everybody. I think I was talking to Sagar, I was talking to, like, a couple of folks, and Indir as well, is that the moment we start with the observation, the moment we have a problem in front of us, our brain just, like.
100xEngineers: very tempted to, like, build something, build a solution out of it, and that's how, like, the human brain is wired, right? So, what I'm trying to, like, tell you all guys is that you have to fight your natural instinct, which is also, like, hard, right? So… but the only thing which I can share here… Let me see if anyone…
100xEngineers: Just give me one sec, I think I need to check.
100xEngineers: the mic…
100xEngineers: Can you guys make sure that, everybody's… On mute right now.
Munish Bhardwaj: I'm able to unmute myself.
100xEngineers: Okay.
100xEngineers: Let me see… let me… Let me just, like, mute…
100xEngineers: Otherwise, it'll have some noise, background noise. Okay, I hope this is fine.
100xEngineers: Cool.
100xEngineers: Yeah, what I was saying is, that…
100xEngineers: this is… this is one of those times when you'll… you'll have that temptation to, like, build solutions, but I would urge you to, like, not do that, because
100xEngineers: the next two months is all about building solutions, right? And the thing is, you guys will come back to that phase, and if you just, like, not focus right now on problem space and on the observation part.
100xEngineers: it's gonna be, like, a same loop. Maybe you build something interesting, but then you realize that this thing was not worth building, and then you go back to the same slate. So, what I'm trying to also share is, like, one of my personal learning is just try to… just try to not, like, do something which everybody does.
100xEngineers: the moment they see a problem, they solve it. Try to spend some time there. Not gonna make this lecture theoretical. I have something interesting planned for you guys, by the way. Like, we are in a, as I said, like, very interesting point in this entire journey. So, for today's lecture.
100xEngineers: I have,
100xEngineers: I've taken a different approach, which I have not done in any of the cohorts, by the way.
100xEngineers: So, it's gonna be, like, something which I'm trying first time, so if it breaks, or if things go wrong, so you can just, like… We'll fall back to the previous, the old tried and tested model.
100xEngineers: But I wanna try it, and hopefully… this is also one of my observations. I want to, like, convert this into an MV plan, so I'm gonna test it with you guys. You guys are my beta testers.
100xEngineers: Today. So let me share my screen, and
100xEngineers: Let me also give you a glimpse of where we stand today before I share this part.
100xEngineers: I hope you guys can see my screen.
100xEngineers: Everyone can see my whiteboard?
100xEngineers: Yes, awesome.
100xEngineers: Yes, I love this book, by the way.
100xEngineers: Fall in love with the problem.
100xEngineers: So we started our journey from, learning about the interfaces, right? And this is where we are. Actually, even before that, we started our journey from here. This is a Module 2 beginning. What to build on the week one, we had our discovery to validation.
100xEngineers: And then we focused from the last week is how do we build things which we have discovered in the week one? And the first principle we learned is that every system exists because
100xEngineers: you have some inputs, and you want to convert it into some desired output, and the job of all of us as AI builders is to identify these inputs, and then identify what is the output that can be valuable to the people who will be using this system.
100xEngineers: And once you solve this part is the step number one, you design systems. And there are multiple parts of this system which we've been learning so far, and we have made quite some progress in the deterministic end. So, in the deterministic part, what we learned is
100xEngineers: we…
100xEngineers: Although it looks like a simple chat app, but it's not a simple app. It takes input, it gives the output back, but there's a lot of things happening in the background. It has a frontend, which stays in my browser, on my client machine, whenever I open it from a mobile, from my laptop.
100xEngineers: And this is the one which interacts with the user. But apart from the app which is downloaded on my browser, there's a bunch of other things which are happening in the backend. There's a large language model which is not sitting on my machine, it's sitting on OpenAI's machine, that's what we call server.
100xEngineers: And this LLM is also a raw file. It doesn't do anything, by itself, like, it can just predict the next word token. So in order for us to use this LLM effectively, we need a system
100xEngineers: And that system is the backend where we store the information. We learned about, like, okay, we also now need to store information here, and that's what we're gonna use, the data storage for.
100xEngineers: So far in this journey, what we have been able to do, and this is a diagram which I
100xEngineers: used in the last code session, but it will be relevant for both code and no code, because both of you, at this point, have
100xEngineers: Understanding of how do we build a system,
100xEngineers: Which takes the input from the end user by building different interfaces.
100xEngineers: For code, you guys have used Gradio and Python. For no code, you have used NATM, Lovable, and a bunch of, like, interesting things you will be learning very soon as well. So, all of you have the capability to now build the user interfaces, which can take some input.
100xEngineers: Although it doesn't need to be a really fancy one. I know some people want to build the most beautiful solution out there, but I would, again, like, force you to,
100xEngineers: like, not…
100xEngineers: go with your natural instinct as of now, but try to, like, solve the MVP version, which is a minimal viable product, and then make it better progressively over time.
100xEngineers: This is what we have done, and then the last week, we learned about the API, how it bridges a second interface with machines.
100xEngineers: So we ended up, like, yesterday, for both code, no code, we learned how to build the backend system, right, with Python, with NATN, and now it connects with our LLM. So we also have this ability to connect different machines, machine-to-machine communication, all the principles that we've been learning so far on the whiteboard. I hope a lot of you can now see how it applies in the practical aspect of it, and you can apply, and you can build things.
100xEngineers: For some of you who are doing it first time, it might take some time, it's completely fine, you might need to re-watch the lectures, you might need to redo the exercise, we have practice sets for that. I'll upload a couple of videos, you'll receive material for that as well, and we'll conduct, the doubt-solving sessions. So, it's okay, take your time if you're somebody who's new, but
100xEngineers: This is a journey which we have covered so far. I'm just giving you a picture of where we stand today.
100xEngineers: we have…
100xEngineers: the ability to build these user interfaces that can take input and generate some output, we can build backends, we can connect it with the LLMs.
100xEngineers: There is one problem, and we did this entire thing with Arav, so we ended up building… so yesterday I built the simple workflow diagnoser app. Looks very ugly, by the way, but it does the job. So, just like what we described on the whiteboard.
100xEngineers: we built this hypothesis for RO. The hypothesis was that we believe ambitious early career professionals in urban India who are AI-aware but know should prove are stuck because they lack a method to convert broad AI possibility onto some specific scoped workflow worth solving.
100xEngineers: So, the hypothesis was that if we provide a structured system to them, which can help them diagnose it, and followed by a guided build sprint, then at least 60% of the active students will be able to identify a real-world problem statement and map it to a workflow, and build a version, and hopefully can present it in the next 90 days.
100xEngineers: By the way, some of you who…
100xEngineers: were not able to understand this problem statement which I'm solving, it's a meta-lesson for this cohort as well.
100xEngineers: every time I use a different problem statement for different cohort, but this time I thought I'll use a problem statement which I can do live and which I can build over these lectures. So every lecture, every part is…
100xEngineers: one of the MBB plans that I have built for Arav, and there are a lot of RFs on this call, so…
100xEngineers: This is also the point where I want to reveal, let the system at an experiment which I'm doing while I'm teaching all of you guys. And while we did this, you guys only played
100xEngineers: a very important role in this experiment, and you gave me the idea of what kind of inputs you need. So this is also the best way to do user interviews. I'm doing user interviews with almost, like, hundreds of people live, while teaching them. So, that's another part.
100xEngineers: Then we discussed the input and output.
100xEngineers: We had the input, which is what Ara will be writing here, the analyst explaining the workflow, so we had some examples.
100xEngineers: Here, I open Jira to check my weekly to-dos, then I'll check High Priority Task, I'll pick one, create a report, send it to my manager on Slack.
100xEngineers: And the example output which we thought would help Arav is that a structured plan that maybe helped him to diagnose the workflow, and then also give you a plan to build those things. And from that.
100xEngineers: hypothesis on whiteboard from a piece of text, to taking decisions on what kind of user interface we should build, how do we take this, should we build a form, chat, and then we built, like, multiple systems around it, we built a simple way to take the input, then we learned how to work with the APIs, and we built the whole system, which… which we saw working live today. So yesterday was, like, I think for both code and no-code track, it was, like.
100xEngineers: concession where you see things built… getting built live, getting, I would say,
100xEngineers: Like, converted from the hypothesis, the text, and the idea in someone's head to something which everyone can touch, can basically use.
100xEngineers: And, you can also distribute these things. So we built API, the diagnose API for Ara, which takes the workflow description, and then it gives the output as a plan, and then we connected this API with a simple interface that can take one input and give output back.
100xEngineers: And, this was connected with Glock, so that's what we have, the three systems, which now we have given picture to the whiteboard.
100xEngineers: As of now, if you understand all of this thing,
100xEngineers: first of all, congratulations, because this is, as I said, something which I took almost, like, 4 years to understand and build, learn all of these parts. Like, before the era of AI, it used to be, like, a whole study of, like.
100xEngineers: like, 3 to 4 years, where people go and learn about these things, build things, and there used to be jobs and companies who used to pay for just this. There are front-end engineers whose only job is to build user interfaces. There are specifically UI engineers as well.
100xEngineers: Although not very relevant these days, but
100xEngineers: I remember, like, one of my friends, it's still relevant, like, not right now, like, in the same number, I won't say that it's irrelevant completely, but it's, like, relevant in very niche, areas, and as we progress.
100xEngineers: I think this… the number will go down, but we have people whose only job is to write
100xEngineers: the programs to build the user interface, the thing which you guys have built here.
100xEngineers: 3 years ago, people used to take salaries as an engineer to do all of these things. I remember, like, when I was doing my first job, I did the sprint planning with my product manager, and we built a chat application that was also one of my first projects.
100xEngineers: Just to build the front end for the chat application, and a couple of screens along with that, we took 4 weeks of time, and we charged the client a good amount of money, and the company paid me, like, a fraction of that as a salary.
100xEngineers: And that's when I realized that… how much money people can make by just building interfaces, right? So, just to giving you a perspective that all of this is actually really, really useful, and it's something which
100xEngineers: earlier was not possible, but the thing is, now you guys understand these things, gives you a leverage, which is different leverage than wipe coding, right? Because now you understand the whole system and you can debug it. So…
100xEngineers: If you do this, first of all, congratulations. I will…
100xEngineers: Now propose you a different set of Questions?
100xEngineers: Hopefully, this is a point where you'll start, like, implementing and making this
100xEngineers: This app, whatever we have built so far, to… to make it production-ready, to make it something which we can start sharing with the end users by end of, like, the next lecture, and you'll have, like, some data with you.
100xEngineers: right now.
100xEngineers: We are at this point where we have built the user interface, the application programming interface, we have connected two machines, we have built our first backend connected with the LLMs.
100xEngineers: Our app can think.
100xEngineers: Now the goal is to teach it how to remember, because this is something which it cannot do.
100xEngineers: We have… All of these parts, right? And I think one thing which I'll explain through this is
100xEngineers: Right now, Araf can type a messy problem statement, and AI types back a clear plan, so it works on the first try.
100xEngineers: Arav is thrilled, but then he closes tab.
100xEngineers: Comes back tomorrow, and every plan, every message, every bit of who said what is simply gone.
100xEngineers: Things which we have discussed here.
100xEngineers: all of these messages, I don't know how many of you remember this, but yesterday we didn't… we didn't actually, like, tested multiple workflows, or persistence specifically, which means if I am giving this app to RF today.
100xEngineers: And, I'll tell him that, hey, you can use it, and let's say he's happy with the plan, but now he forgot to save this somewhere, or copy this plan somewhere, and he refreshed this page, or maybe he closed the browser, came back again. He won't be able to see this.
100xEngineers: Because we are not storing it, Arav is not storing it, and the entire plan is gone. And now we have to, like, again generate, and again pay for that generation.
100xEngineers: This is one of the problems with our current application. It… what I call it, the amnesia problem statement. It…
100xEngineers: has… it doesn't have any memory, just like how a person who has the disease of amnesia cannot remember anything. That is the exact state of our application.
100xEngineers: So we are going to fix it, and in order for us to fix it, I'm also introducing you an interesting skill called Domain Modeling. We'll talk more about it.
100xEngineers: Before we, we, we discuss this. But, I'll… I can actually, like…
100xEngineers: just skip this part, because we have already shown you the application. This was something which I did as a part of
100xEngineers: the interactive slides, so all of you can actually interact with these kind of slides. I'll share the link right after the second half of this lecture. I don't want to share this link right now, because you guys can then
100xEngineers: look at the answers, and you can, like, some of you can just, like, I would say, proceed to the next exercises. I want everyone to, like, go through the concepts. I'll ask you some questions, and at the end of first half, I'll share the link, and we're gonna perform a practice set on this interactive slide sessions, which
100xEngineers: I've been building for this particular lecture.
100xEngineers: As I said, Arabs app right now has Amnesia. We have a good chat interface ready with us, which means I can send a message here. It's just like a simulation of what our app does. But the problem is, if we restart the server, if we restart the browser, everything is gone.
100xEngineers: And, the reason for this is that everything is running on a program that holds
100xEngineers: all of this information in a temporary variable. What we call this is… it's an in-memory data, storage. What is in-memory means? You guys have heard of this technology, or this,
100xEngineers: thing called RAG? Actually, sorry, RAM.
100xEngineers: I'm getting confused between.
100xEngineers: I forgot I'm living… I live in India, so RAM also means other things as well.
100xEngineers: I need to… Do random access memory.
100xEngineers: A random access memory is the computer's short-term memory bank.
100xEngineers: It temporarily holds the active data instructions that your CPU needs right now, because it is volatile. All the data in RAM is erased the moment your device is powered off and rebooted.
100xEngineers: If you are buying RAM, or if you bought RAM in the past, this is how the RAM chip looks. The different
100xEngineers: type of RAMs which are available. And suddenly why I shifted from talking about amnesia problem and data problem to RAM is because this is the level 1 of data storage. Whenever we install
100xEngineers: Any application, or we run an application even on a browser.
100xEngineers: our operating system allocates some RAM to it. If you have seen your activity monitor, I don't know how many of you
100xEngineers: are nerdy about these things, but I am a lot. If I open this… let me open this here…
100xEngineers: You guys can see, hopefully, this is my activity monitor on,
100xEngineers: Mac right now, and you can see, like, Google Chrome itself is taking up 719.3 MB of memory.
100xEngineers: This is the memory thread, and
100xEngineers: There's Zoom, which is taking another 683, but even, like, more than Zoom, Google is taking right now. And the reason why Google has, or Google Chrome, sorry, has…
100xEngineers: I occupied more than 720MB of RAM on my PC is because I am running multiple browser tabs. So I have, like, one of this tab, I have another tab, which is working, and then there's, like, a couple of other tabs on the other screen.
100xEngineers: Each and every tab has an application.
100xEngineers: Each and every application has some data which is living there.
100xEngineers: And the things which are getting processed, let's say, right now, if I send this hay.
100xEngineers: this particular data is getting stored in the RAM right now.
100xEngineers: So the more data I put on my browsers, on my apps, on my screens, the more it has to put in into the RAM. That's also another reason why your Google Chrome or any browser eats up majority of the RAM space, because
100xEngineers: everything what you see there, every data which is coming in from these apps, this gets, like, like, I would say installed and loaded on… on these… these random access memory. And this is the memory, which is, as I said, it's… it's a temporary one.
100xEngineers: So, it, it only…
100xEngineers: stores the information. It's a short-term memory bank for a computer until the CPU needs it, and when you power off it as a device, or maybe you, like, refresh it, if I close the, all the tabs of my Chrome today, it will just free up all the space.
100xEngineers: why it is important? Because, as I said, this is the by default way of how our programs are built, and this is how the small, I would say the in-memory database work, the term for this is called in-memory, which is both, it means the data is living in the memory.
100xEngineers: And the memory dies as the program stops.
100xEngineers: So what we have just…
100xEngineers: learned here is that we need a place outside of this random access memory, outside of this RAM,
100xEngineers: But a place to put things, I would say…
100xEngineers: Until you know the shape of your data. Until you know what exactly you want to store.
100xEngineers: it's useless. So, what I want to, like, share here is that I can tell you, like, different ways. Maybe we can buy another device. We can have, like.
100xEngineers: SDD, something called as, like.
100xEngineers: hard disks, drives, so this is also a place where you can store the information, right? We can have, like, multiple of disks, you can have SSDs, you can have even cloud storage. All of these things are great, but the thing is, if you don't know what kind of data you want to store.
100xEngineers: You'll never be able to make the decision, first of all, how much memory do you need?
100xEngineers: This is going one level deeper than the VIP coding stuff, and which will be helping you to understand the data architecture and designing systems for databases.
100xEngineers: first thing we need to understand for Arab's application, and both for your application, is that what kind of data we have, what is the shape of this data, and what are the important things we should store, because not everything needs to be stored in our permanent memory. There are a few things which
100xEngineers: I don't mind, like, letting it on the temporary memory, which is on RAM. Let's say if there is a status, like, server is running, right? Definitely server is running is a… is a good
100xEngineers: indicator, but I don't want to store this
100xEngineers: flag every time on my database, right? It's just a temporary signal that my server is running, and whenever it is not running, I'll just, like, send another variable here. But I definitely want to store the information of these messages.
100xEngineers: Because this is what's important to Arav and for me, right? If I… if Arav is writing a prompt, and then I'm generating a plan from the ALM, that is useful, because that is also something which is generated by the ALM, and I'm paying for that generation. So I would rather use that and store that, so Arav can take a look at it. But,
100xEngineers: That is the important skill, which we're gonna focus on. So…
100xEngineers: Before we start building anything data storage system.
100xEngineers: We look at how to understand what kind of things we will be storing, and how to decide what is the decision-making framework here.
100xEngineers: Can anyone give me an answer of this? This is a quick pause and think question for all of you.
100xEngineers: We are discussing about RO's problem statement, and we understood The problem right now…
100xEngineers: And why the message is not getting stored? Because it's in the temporary storage.
100xEngineers: where could the plan go? Where could that particular plan… because we also understand that plan is very important, that's originated from the LM.
100xEngineers: Where could that plan go so that it survives the tap closing? Any thoughts, any suggestions for this?
100xEngineers: Must be an easy one, I think a lot of you have.
100xEngineers: Heard about these terms.
100xEngineers: Yes?
100xEngineers: Definitely, I think some people who are mentioning the nuances and the specification, I love this. It definitely needs to be stored. On the back end. We cannot afford to store all the information to front-end, right?
100xEngineers: Maybe front-end can keep a copy of the plan, but definitely need to store it in the backend. In the backend also, we need to store it in database. That's what we… we learned in the first lecture. So it's a data storage system, right?
100xEngineers: I would not introduce cash right now,
100xEngineers: song right now, I think, if I'm pronouncing her name correct. But, again, the thing is, we'll go from point A to point B. These are the destinations which we'll be reached in maybe, like, next couple of weeks.
100xEngineers: But I won't start with cache, I won't start with something which is, like, more advanced today. I think I was discussing yesterday that over-engineering has killed
100xEngineers: I think they… I think, say, a majority number of projects, and also
100xEngineers: developer's time, as far as I know, and as far as I can relate with my career. So, the goal is also, like, to…
100xEngineers: find clarity and simplicity when we're building solutions. Persistent storage is the right answer, backend server, stored…
100xEngineers: local storage.
100xEngineers: You can do local storage, but the problem is if somebody has deleted the browser. Let's say, for now, I delete the browser. Everything which is stored in the local storage of the browser is also deleted.
100xEngineers: So yeah, that's… that's a thing.
100xEngineers: Now, just to reveal the answer, yes, it has to go somewhere. It has to be outside of the program, a place on the disk that keeps
100xEngineers: Existing after the code stops.
100xEngineers: So if you're talking about…
100xEngineers: your computer, it's a hard disk, STD, cloud storage. That is also, like, a hard disk on someone else's computer, by the way. But a disk which stores the permanent information, and for that, we have
100xEngineers: these long-term memory solutions, your hard disk and STDs.
100xEngineers: On that place, we also need to store this information with an application. We can't just randomly throw everything there. We need an app. We need a system, and that system is known as database.
100xEngineers: But a database is users, as I said, until you can answer one thing, which is that what shape is the thing I am storing? A plan, a message, a user.
100xEngineers: I have a question to all of you. This is Arav's situation. We have built an application.
100xEngineers: We have given this to RF.
100xEngineers: He can write and explain the workflow.
100xEngineers: One of the examples is, I keep starting AI site projects, installing, help me pick one, and actually ship it. Then our AI can generate a demo plan, this is a sample, plan like this.
100xEngineers: Look at this application.
100xEngineers: And I want you to understand what are the things in it, what does each thing have, and how do they connect? Three questions. Because the goal of this
100xEngineers: is… We cannot store what we cannot describe.
100xEngineers: The step number one is to describe what
100xEngineers: Are we seeing on the app? What are the things which we need to store?
100xEngineers: How does each and everything, connect with each other? And how can we describe
100xEngineers: each of them. Let's do one by one, because I know three questions can get confusing. Let's try to understand what are the things. Things are so-called parts of this entire project which you will be storing, which you will be saving in the filter storage.
100xEngineers: What do you think? Based on this, what are the things you will be storing? Message?
100xEngineers: Yeah. Like, prompt and output prompt message is the same part.
100xEngineers: Context?
100xEngineers: I would put context, input, output, and message in the same thing, because message is also… like, in this bubble, everything is a message to me, like, whatever in this plan.
100xEngineers: The only differentiation is that this is the message which is sent by Arav, this is the message which is sent by our AI assistant.
100xEngineers: But…
100xEngineers: Essentially, both of these are message. So, I agree, people who are saying message, context, input-output prompts, we need to store that. This is one of THE things.
100xEngineers: Anything else?
100xEngineers: Session details like start time, end time, pause time.
100xEngineers: Yeah, that's a good nuance.
100xEngineers: I'm not sure, like, what will I do with this data right now, but can definitely help in future, if I have multiple of conversation with Arav.
100xEngineers: Chat session details, timestamps, chat header, RS query prompt, LM's response.
100xEngineers: Structure and tone, very interesting, Yash.
100xEngineers: Yes, structure and tone is something which is also hidden Quality of this output.
100xEngineers: What do you think? What's the… what's the tone for this output?
100xEngineers: I would say it's not very formal, it's slightly on the casual side.
100xEngineers: It's too vague, it's casual, right? It's… there's actually, like, it's actually a dummy prompt, but just the looks of it,
100xEngineers: the overall style of this plan is very casual, so I can describe the… Tone and, style of…
100xEngineers: how the LM will respond. I can make it more professional, I can make it descriptive, I can make it concise, I can make it casual.
100xEngineers: That is but a very, very interesting insight, by the way.
100xEngineers: So… Kudos to Yash.
100xEngineers: Now, these 3 questions, which I asked you guys, and well, actually, like, we just, like, had the first one about the things.
100xEngineers: The messages, maybe the tonality and all of these things.
100xEngineers: The message can become a candidate, for… an entity.
100xEngineers: An entity is a very specific keyword for our discussion. Just remember this, this is gonna be helpful for the next part.
100xEngineers: These entities will help you to make sense of what kind of things, what kind of…
100xEngineers: items you have in your program that you want to store, that you want to save. And a lot of these things revolve around these entities. Like, entities can connect with different entities. Entities will also have
100xEngineers: some… attributes which define what this entity looks like. And let's do a quick check for this.
100xEngineers: All of you are correct when you said that message is one of those things that we definitely want to store. That's the answer to the first question. And there are multiple others, but I'll stick to message for now, as of now, to take one example.
100xEngineers: So this could become one entity, which definitely we need to store.
100xEngineers: How can you describe this message?
100xEngineers: Some people were mentioning that we can have a time, which is a timestamp when this message sent, or when I received the message from the ALM.
100xEngineers: Then we discussed about the tone and the structure, that is what Yash has mentioned here.
100xEngineers: Now, I have a quick follow-up question on that.
100xEngineers: This is to Yush and to everybody else.
100xEngineers: Do you think the structure and tone?
100xEngineers: is an entity.
100xEngineers: Yes and no.
100xEngineers: Think about it.
100xEngineers: No?
100xEngineers: Read this line again, like, read these three questions again.
100xEngineers: What does each thing have in this thing? We have messages.
100xEngineers: So, first thing, just replace this thing with message as an answer. What does each message have? Each message have time, each message have a tone.
100xEngineers: a structure.
100xEngineers: The structure of this message is casual. It's written in a casual tone, with this one also written in a casual tone.
100xEngineers: This is the thing. The structure and the tone is the thing that message Has.
100xEngineers: These are the facts.
100xEngineers: That makes a message what a message is.
100xEngineers: So this becomes an attribute.
100xEngineers: Do you agree with me, Yash?
100xEngineers: Yes.
100xEngineers: So, that's exactly how we think about the attributes. So, I hope you…
100xEngineers: get the clarity on message and the structure, message and tone. I would use the structure tone interchangeably.
100xEngineers: Message is our first entity in this process. We understand that we need to store the message, but we also need to define what is a message and what are the things that makes message a message. We need to understand when this message is received, when this message is generated, so there would be a time attached to it. Time will become another attribute, because it defines that this message has a timestamp.
100xEngineers: This message will have a tone that again becomes an attribute of this message.
100xEngineers: Now, while I do all of this, I actually keep my whiteboard on the other screen, so we can just come back to it.
100xEngineers: No session of mine can finish without whiteboard. So we have just declared one very important part. That message, this is our entity number one.
100xEngineers: for Arab's application.
100xEngineers: I'll be using some attributes here, so… These are the attributes.
100xEngineers: What were the attributes we discussed? We discussed about the time.
100xEngineers: When the message is sent. And there could be, like, different type of time as well, like the, the time at which we send the message, time at which we generate the plan, the message it got delivered.
100xEngineers: all of these things, but I'll keep time to keep things simple. Then we have tone slash structure. Actually, I'll keep tone for now, keeping it simple.
100xEngineers: Is there anything else we can keep for message as the attribute? This is where you can get creative.
100xEngineers: What is meant by attributes? Attributes is something which defines the message, which defines your entity.
100xEngineers: What makes a message message?
100xEngineers: A message can be casual.
100xEngineers: Adjectives.
100xEngineers: in English grammar, what we tell, what gives the quality of a particular noun. So that is exactly what, attributes are doing, but for these things which exist in our database, or which we will be storing in a database. What we're trying to do here is we're trying to find the shape of our data.
100xEngineers: So, first thing, we need to understand what are the things we need to store in database. We looked at Arab's chat window, and we definitely know that there are messages, so we'll be storing messages as a key part in our database. Now, the thing is, what makes this message a message? What are the things you will be storing against this message?
100xEngineers: What will tell us the quality of these messages?
100xEngineers: So I hope you get it.
100xEngineers: what kind of information you want. It depends, again, what kind of app you are building, what kind of solution you are building, and that's why everything boils down to the…
100xEngineers: Thing that you guys have done in the week one?
100xEngineers: And that's where you will realize that the more time you have spent, the thing which I opened in this lecture, I opened the lecture with, the more time you spend with problem statements, the more time you understand
100xEngineers: To discover the right inputs, the problem statements, the validation, talking to users.
100xEngineers: the more easy it will become for you to do all of these exercises which I'm telling you.
100xEngineers: as of now, if you have done enough number of interviews, enough number of, like, research, you already know that we definitely need to store the message. I'm just giving the reference for my example, but you know this very well with your example as well, you can think about it, and I'll give you a practice set after this. So…
100xEngineers: And then what things define for this attribute. So a lot of interesting answers, by the way, in the chat. So, we have,
100xEngineers: Messages, message ID,
100xEngineers: Sender type? Yes. Although, as of now, I think I'll keep one type of sender only, because…
100xEngineers: I have RF for now. First, I'll solve for RF, but yes, you're right, if I want to scale this application, I might have different type of senders, different type of people who will be messaging,
100xEngineers: ness… I would rather use something called roll.
100xEngineers: instead of doing sender type here, for, like, what Hunch has mentioned, because role will help me to define whether each and every message is
100xEngineers: from my user, which is the RF, or from the… assistant.
100xEngineers: This is a very similar thing what we have done, and what we have seen in the,
100xEngineers: LLM API call, if you remember that. They're also, like, ChatGPD and all the LLMs, use role as one of the attributes to define that what kind of message is this? Is it a message sent by user, assistant? They also have something called system.
100xEngineers: In our case, we only need two things. Maybe you can have, like, more than these two roles if you're building for your application, but
100xEngineers: Just think about it, right? And,
100xEngineers: now you can also have… yeah, I think one thing which I like from… and I'm gonna steal from Han's answer, is the content, because message does…
100xEngineers: definitely needs to have content. If message does not have a content, then… it… Doesn't make any sense.
100xEngineers: With only time, tone, and role, I can't do anything with the message. This is the first…
100xEngineers: shape of our data point, which is the message. And this is how we can describe one message.
100xEngineers: Definitely, it's not complete. You can spend more time, you can, like, add more attributes, and you can, like, do this. When… when do we stop this?
100xEngineers: The idea is first to write down everything which you know, and then we perform this exercise, which I'm gonna perform with all of you, and we'll go it progressively. You don't need to complete everything, you need to write all of these things on day one. It's okay to miss some of the attributes, it's okay to miss some entities.
100xEngineers: If you're starting out, but over time, the more activity you do, this part, the discussion, which we are doing, it will help you to think about what are the important attributes you can store, right? So this…
100xEngineers: This helps you to build that muscle.
100xEngineers: Everybody got this part, right? What is entity and what is attribute? I hope we can move to the next thing, because only if this is clear, then it will make sense for us to answer the second question.
100xEngineers: Yes, actually, Sagar, can you describe exactly what are the things which you're unclear about? I'll give you a definition of entity and the attributes.
100xEngineers: Entities are the things which we're gonna store in our database. And now you'll say, like, we're gonna store everything, but we have to start with
100xEngineers: a key element, right? This key element could be a message, it could be a plan, it could be, like, this entire chat window, whatever you store, whatever you do with your app, right? So, these are the things, right, the things which you have in your
100xEngineers: application.
100xEngineers: with the example of Arabs application, we don't have a lot of things. So when we opened the Arabs app, that's why I shared this screenshot, we only have messages and chat window here.
100xEngineers: So the core thing that we want to store as an information, a key point, is this message.
100xEngineers: And that's… that's the thing which becomes the entity. Now.
100xEngineers: it can get confusing, because now you'll think about what is an attribute, because we are also storing the attribute. So this is a good point to discuss and maybe, like, understand
100xEngineers: Attributes are the…
100xEngineers: qualities which makes this entity an entity, which means that if I am… if I'm deciding to store messages
100xEngineers: in my database.
100xEngineers: can I just put, like, a random message, and will it make sense? Just think about it, like, if I'm building a database right now, and let's say I've got these two entities, and I'll actually show this
100xEngineers: to you guys, let me open Sheets… Google Sheets. So, I have…
100xEngineers: This is how database looks like, by the way. Just like a spreadsheet. So I have… Messages.
100xEngineers: And I'm gonna store messages here. The first message is this, and then second message is also this. Maybe this will help to visualize
100xEngineers: The entities and attributes.
100xEngineers: So we decided the messages were our…
100xEngineers: Key entity, and now we started storing all the information.
100xEngineers: Let's say we end up building this entire system, and we're gonna use
100xEngineers: our spreadsheets as a database. So we're gonna have all those messages here.
100xEngineers: Do you think, first of all, it will make sense if now I have to…
100xEngineers: if I have, like, out of closed the browser, out of closed my application, and he is coming back, can I just directly use all of this data?
100xEngineers: In the same way, like, how it was presented, and how it will make sense.
100xEngineers: But I think I want to, like, answer this to people who are, like, confused between entities and attributes. First, let's try to, like, understand this part. I hope you got it. We have a message, we define that we want to store message as a key information in our database, and we store that, we have two messages.
100xEngineers: Do you think this is enough?
100xEngineers: First of all, this is enough.
100xEngineers: Or not.
100xEngineers: No, right? What is missing here?
100xEngineers: What is missing? What… why this… why just storing the messages like this is not enough?
100xEngineers: Question 2.
100xEngineers: Sagar, Yasir, and anyone who is… confused here.
100xEngineers: What do you think? What do we need?
100xEngineers: Yes, we need who is the user?
100xEngineers: We need a context.
100xEngineers: We need the type also, because we need to know what type of this message, maybe language.
100xEngineers: Because, yes, someone can write in a different language.
100xEngineers: Yes, exactly, Samir, you are correct, you are exactly correct.
100xEngineers: Yes, I think if you got the… got my point right, and I want to understand it from, like, people who are confused, that
100xEngineers: Do you know why storing messages is not enough?
100xEngineers: And what extra things we need in order for us to make sense of the message that we are storing. All these extra things, these are the attributes which define our message, which makes it easy for us to store the information. So tomorrow, if I want to read this file, if I want to gather the same messages and show it to Arav, I can tell that, hey, this is a message which is sent by Arav.
100xEngineers: Because I can read my, spreadsheet, or the database, wherever I'm storing this, and the context was… this was a conversation, maybe we can add
100xEngineers: The conversation, about…
100xEngineers: Like, discovery. This is what we can mention. This is a type of, a regular message, a normal message. Nothing's fancy with this message. Maybe in future we can have different type of message. The language is English.
100xEngineers: Now, with these attributes, we can define this one message, and we know exactly where to put this message in our window.
100xEngineers: This is a message which is sent by an AI assistant, so this is the assistant's message.
100xEngineers: What is the context? The context is, it's a reply. It's the same normal type of message, same English. So we are now defining our message.
100xEngineers: Things which define our message.
100xEngineers: This becomes our attribute.
100xEngineers: Timestamp could be another attribute, which tells us at exactly at what time This message was sent.
100xEngineers: Straight of the message, yes, you're all right.
100xEngineers: Is it clear? Is it clear to, everybody who… who had, like, confusion around it? Like, why this is a message, and why these are… these are things which are entities?
100xEngineers: Very clear. I'll try to make this entire sheet also very clear, is that this Will be message content.
100xEngineers: One thing which I'll help you to…
100xEngineers: Makes sense right now, is that all of these things, which are the Title of these columns.
100xEngineers: Title of this column.
100xEngineers: All of these are attributes. A quick hack.
100xEngineers: for people who are still confused, or maybe who… who wants to, like, look at it from a different lens. Each and everything which you see on the column title.
100xEngineers: is the attribute.
100xEngineers: We have this call sheet.
100xEngineers: This is the sheet number 1. I'll change the name of this sheet, and I'll call this sheet Message.
100xEngineers: Why do I want to call this sheet a message? Because this sheet describes what my message looks like.
100xEngineers: Which means it gives a very good… Analogy to our sheets.
100xEngineers: To our mental models.
100xEngineers: Whenever you design a sheet, which is a table.
100xEngineers: I'll introduce a term called table. This is what a tabulist data structure, right?
100xEngineers: This table represents a message. It has a message content, it has a user who is sending this message, it has some context about it, type, language, time.
100xEngineers: XYZ.
100xEngineers: This is the entity. This is the attribute. All of these things are the attributes.
100xEngineers: Does that make it clear?
100xEngineers: Is there anything thing as entity other than message here?
100xEngineers: Yes.
100xEngineers: A lot of those things, and we'll… we'll explore, we'll explore.
100xEngineers: But I hope you got the… got the distinction between these two things.
100xEngineers: Cool, well, let's move to the next part.
100xEngineers: The last question.
100xEngineers: Now we understand.
100xEngineers: Actually, before I come to the last question.
100xEngineers: I'll also put one more example on this whiteboard, so that it makes sense.
100xEngineers: For us to, like, take this.
100xEngineers: This is also what Sagar said. Are there any other things in this
100xEngineers: Application which we need to store.
100xEngineers: Yes.
100xEngineers: There are…
100xEngineers: There are users.
100xEngineers: This entire application is used by AROV.
100xEngineers: Who is Arav? Arav is a user.
100xEngineers: Today, we are solving this problem for ARF, but I definitely don't want to limit it to the RF itself. The moment it gives the plan for ARP, I also want to test it with multiple other people who are facing the same problem.
100xEngineers: So there will be number of users. Arab is not only gonna be the one single person for which I'm gonna build the entire app.
100xEngineers: So definitely, this is the another thing which we want to store.
100xEngineers: Because if there would be, like, more of ROVs in my application, or people who will be using my apps, I need to store the information about them. What makes this user a user?
100xEngineers: Can we do a quick… Brainstorming on this.
100xEngineers: The second entity of our application.
100xEngineers: is user, which means we need to store information about user. What do we need?
100xEngineers: Username?
100xEngineers: Yes, we need a name for this user. We can call it username or name, I'll just…
100xEngineers: Keep the name for now.
100xEngineers: Age?
100xEngineers: Location, although I don't know what will I do with the location part, but I definitely need email ID.
100xEngineers: I would say having email ID would help, so I can connect.
100xEngineers: R… ID? Actually, ID, I'll come to it, but, gender, we can have all of these things.
100xEngineers: If we are making it…
100xEngineers: as somebody suggested right now, if you are making it an application which needs a login or sign-up mechanism, we need a password as well, so we need email ID and password. As of now, I'm not doing it.
100xEngineers: So, I'll remove this. Now, this is also a place where you start thinking about your app in general.
100xEngineers: it might look like that, hey, we are just discussing a few things here and there, but we are also describing and designing the whole architecture of our application from these terms. Because we're deciding that, do we need an authentication right now? If yes, then I might need to store the password. But if not, then I might not do that. So, it's…
100xEngineers: it is the first step of, like, architecting your data system. So, there could be, like, multiple attributes, I'll keep it to this for now, the minimal set of ones. So, we have two examples, and now you can come back to the same thing which I had here.
100xEngineers: How would I express the user here?
100xEngineers: Somebody… something has already been… already used here.
100xEngineers: But I need to describe user.
100xEngineers: What is the best way for me to, like, add more categories? Should I, like, add things in bracket here? Should I just, like, mention this is RO's age, and it's gonna be…
100xEngineers: like, 28 years old, mail, things. Is that a best way for me to store information about my users?
100xEngineers: Now, right? How can we store the information? Separate sheet in the workbook, yes. Awesome, I love it.
100xEngineers: Somebody is getting it.
100xEngineers: So, we'll create one more sheet.
100xEngineers: What should we call this sheet?
100xEngineers: User, yes, or users.
100xEngineers: Hardcall user right now.
100xEngineers: What is the column name for this?
100xEngineers: Username, or name.
100xEngineers: then age, and basically all the attributes which we discussed here become the column name for this. Email ID.
100xEngineers: gender…
100xEngineers: So all of this becomes the column ID. And now I have multiple users. I have one user's… one user who have ROP, maybe, let's say, H28, email ID, I'll…
100xEngineers: Aravatmail.com.
100xEngineers: Gender is male.
100xEngineers: And then I have, one more person, let's say I myself am using it, Sudanth, and I'll write my age.
100xEngineers: 29, and I'll write the email.
100xEngineers: Say that male, and then gender.
100xEngineers: So, I have Nick, no, multiple people.
100xEngineers: Let's say there is one more person whose name is also Siddhant.
100xEngineers: Jose is also 29.
100xEngineers: And, he has… The email, but slightly different one.
100xEngineers: But everything else is the same.
100xEngineers: Now, at this point, Email is the only thing which is helping us to…
100xEngineers: Discriminate between these two values, because everything else is same.
100xEngineers: We can use email to identify these people, but it's not the most reliable method, because tomorrow, if, let's say, this Siddhan actually changes the email.
100xEngineers: let's say… he…
100xEngineers: for some reason, not able to, like, continue the service of whatever email he was using. Let's say he was using Gmail, but right now, he got a plan from his company, and he canceled the Gmail, and now he's on Microsoft, or maybe Outlook, and he's not using the older one.
100xEngineers: And he has not told any… anyone, so we are trying to reach to sit at 2 at…
100xEngineers: I would say Gmail.
100xEngineers: It will, again, create some confusion for us, because this is the only thing which is, like, helping us to,
100xEngineers: Discriminate and contact this person.
100xEngineers: So we can't… in a way, it is unique, but it is not the most reliable source.
100xEngineers: So, one other thing which we need here is some kind of unique identification, because there can be different entries in my user table, which can share the same name, same age, maybe same gender as well.
100xEngineers: Right? Maybe, like, let's say they are not okay sharing the email. Let's say both of them said, hey, I don't want to disclose my information. I just want to see the plan.
100xEngineers: And I'll say, okay, I don't want, like, to breach anyone's privacy if they are not okay. Only then I'll ask, if you're not okay, I'll just at least let you do the trial. But for trial also, I need to store the information, right?
100xEngineers: And let's say if these two guys decided not to share the email, then I don't have anything which can…
100xEngineers: Help me identify who is the different one.
100xEngineers: So, this is where the concept of
100xEngineers: unique identifier comes in. So what I'll do is I'll create one more row here.
100xEngineers: I'll just, like, mention the user ID here. Very common term, I hope, like, nothing fancy here, as of now.
100xEngineers: So, I'll just, like, give the IDs to every user, and now I can describe. So, when I talk about, like, this person has started a chat, or this person has sent a message, I would rather use the user ID, too. This is how the whole ID system works, any kind of, like, in database.
100xEngineers: Simple one, but I just want to, like, make sure that you understand it for why we need a specific table here for user ID. Now, coming back to
100xEngineers: This thing. Yeah, I'll not introduce the terms right now, but I'll use these terms.
100xEngineers: We have these two tables.
100xEngineers: Which we have just described on our whiteboard as well.
100xEngineers: The third question, and the third, and one of the most important questions, is this entire database design, or data design.
100xEngineers: Exercise is that… How do these things
100xEngineers: When I say things, it means how do messages and users connect with each other?
100xEngineers: What are their relationship?
100xEngineers: Committed.
100xEngineers: Situationship.
100xEngineers: Long term, short term.
100xEngineers: We need to understand, right? Maybe…
100xEngineers: Right now, we don't know it. As of now, we need to understand, like, what is the way how I can connect my… this entity to this, because there is a connection.
100xEngineers: Which I can see.
100xEngineers: And let's… let's… let's try to, like, understand it from the same… Spreadsheet example.
100xEngineers: So, we have a message, and we have a user. So, earlier you were using a username.
100xEngineers: We're calling it user, but it was actually username.
100xEngineers: This was the same field which we had here.
100xEngineers: Now, as of now, usually the, I would say if I store all the messages in one chat, or in one sheet, I will also have, let's say, one more entry, but…
100xEngineers: this one of, let's say, Siddhant.
100xEngineers: And then I can have, like, another one from another Siddhanth.
100xEngineers: Now this table becomes confusing to me.
100xEngineers: Because it is not helping me to uniquely identify
100xEngineers: This message is sent by which Siddhanth, because I have two Siddhanth.
100xEngineers: Maybe this… these two are sent by the same person, maybe from… by different people.
100xEngineers: So, that's…
100xEngineers: where we need to find the user ID, the thing which we have just discussed, the unique identification. So instead of using the name, I would use the user ID.
100xEngineers: Does that make sense, first of all, to people who are following along? If anyone has an objection or a questionnaire, please do ask.
100xEngineers: Do you understand why user ID makes sense, and why name will become confusing? Yes? Awesome, that's great.
100xEngineers: Okay, so we have the user ID. Now, this user ID
100xEngineers: Let me just, like, change the user IDs here.
100xEngineers: I'll keep the user ID of Assistant 0, and for everyone else, this 2, and this 3. Now we can uniquely identify.
100xEngineers: Did you see what we did here?
100xEngineers: We are now…
100xEngineers: telling that if I have to look at this table, and if I'm just looking at, let's say, this message.
100xEngineers: I can tell that who sent this message.
100xEngineers: by looking at the user ID, and then I can search this user ID in another sheet.
100xEngineers: Because I can uniquely identify all the IDs, so I can look at one, and I can see the name, and I can tell that this message is sent by Arav, because the Arav's user ID is 1 in our sheet.
100xEngineers: What this is telling us, it is telling us how these two different entities, two different things in our data system is connected to each other, how they are connected.
100xEngineers: They're connected by the user ID. So that's…
100xEngineers: One of the key parts here.
100xEngineers: So, one thing which I'm gonna add here is that
100xEngineers: user… ID?
100xEngineers: And I'm gonna add the user ID here as well.
100xEngineers: Just like what we added user ID, we also need a message ID, because messages can be unique as well.
100xEngineers: And I'll reflect it back on our message part, just like this. I'll add one column, and I call this
100xEngineers: Message ID.
100xEngineers: And then I'll have these 1, 2… 3 and 4.
100xEngineers: Okay, so we have, like, message IDs, and we have message, content.
100xEngineers: Now… we can, say that this is connected. These two things are connected.
100xEngineers: And how they are connected? Because the user ID is same in both of these two spreadsheets. We just saw there.
100xEngineers: All these user IDs, they point out to the same user, and we can tell that who sent this message by looking at the user ID. That is a connection point.
100xEngineers: But there's also one more way to describe this relationship, which is
100xEngineers: How many users can send how many messages?
100xEngineers: Or can I just look at this and say.
100xEngineers: Araf can send only one message?
100xEngineers: Or can Arav send more than one message?
100xEngineers: Can you tell me that by just looking at this table?
100xEngineers: Like, unless until you have entries here, you can't tell it.
100xEngineers: We'll say right now you only have one entry for RF.
100xEngineers: It's gonna be difficult.
100xEngineers: to predict whether ARF can send more messages or not.
100xEngineers: I run this until you see the entries.
100xEngineers: But ideally, we know that the app which we are building, Arab is allowed to send multiple messages.
100xEngineers: Right?
100xEngineers: And that's the reason why we picked the chat as an interface, because we wanted it to be an interface that can support follow-up conversations. So if Arav has a confusion about this workflow, Arav should be able to ask a follow-up message, which means one user can have multiple messages.
100xEngineers: So, what I'll do, actually, I'll…
100xEngineers: put it here to make it slightly easier to visualize. This is the one message entity.
100xEngineers: But…
100xEngineers: If I take the values from this message.
100xEngineers: For now, I'll just… let's say… You fill these…
100xEngineers: All attributes with each and every value.
100xEngineers: There can be, like, multiple… Messages…
100xEngineers: Which can share different attributes, but all of these messages can belong to the same user.
100xEngineers: Everybody agrees to this?
100xEngineers: Yes?
100xEngineers: Do you think the opposite is also true?
100xEngineers: Do you think opposite of this true? Which means, can… one message…
100xEngineers: Be sent by two different users.
100xEngineers: Can I draw a table like this, where I say that this is the one message.
100xEngineers: And, it is sent by two different users.
100xEngineers: Like this and this. Maybe Siddhant and both, Aro.
100xEngineers: Nope.
100xEngineers: Why not?
100xEngineers: I can write same message like this.
100xEngineers: Hey, I opened Jira, and RF can write the same message. Maybe we do the same job.
100xEngineers: So we can have the same message content.
100xEngineers: No, the attributes will be different.
100xEngineers: I love it. I love the people who are thinking along with me, because this is the exact same thought process which I was expecting.
100xEngineers: You guys are right.
100xEngineers: Even if I write the same content, the message will be different.
100xEngineers: the entire entity, and the reason why we have attributes, more than one attribute, content is not the only thing. We have the troll, we have the time, we have the message, we have the user ID, we have all of these things which can change. Even the content can remain the same, but things which describe a message.
100xEngineers: are more than just content. And we don't want one message which is gonna be exact replica that is linked with two different user IDs.
100xEngineers: We don't want this table, where I have this message, which is linked by 1,2.
100xEngineers: Because this is confusing.
100xEngineers: This is really confusing, and this is also a best practice when we design databases. We don't do these kind of things. We don't put commas in the column. Ideally, this is something which we'll learn as we start building it, but for now.
100xEngineers: This… this is something which we don't want, because we… it'll create problems for us in future, and we won't be able to understand that when we are looking at the data, that who is the actual owner of this
100xEngineers: Message.
100xEngineers: And logically also, it doesn't make sense, because every message which is sent by a user needs to be unique. So, what this entire thing tells us, what… what is a learning for this… for us after answering these three questions.
100xEngineers: we need entities.
100xEngineers: These are things which we store in our database, which we're gonna store, because these things are valuable. These things will help us to build the application, make it persistent, make it, like, have an experience so that people can close the app and come back and still have the same value. These are the things which we're gonna store.
100xEngineers: The second thing is there would be attributes, which… because we can't just store the content.
100xEngineers: Because we tried that. If we just store the content, we won't be able to identify who sent this message. So we need more things to describe each and every message. The content, the user ID, who sent this message, what was the role of that person, the tone, the time, the message ID, all of these.
100xEngineers: these becomes the attributes. And the third thing is.
100xEngineers: How these different entities are connected.
100xEngineers: Two ways to define the relationship. One is the common attribute. There needs to be a common attribute always. Whenever there is a conversation about
100xEngineers: Relationship. Defining relationship between two different entities. Defining relationship between a user and a message, we need a common table.
100xEngineers: So that we can refer it, and we can connect the dots between two different tables and two different sheets.
100xEngineers: This common table, or sorry, common column, is known as Porinki.
100xEngineers: Why it's known as foreign key is because this
100xEngineers: Is the key which will help two tables to connect with each other.
100xEngineers: For now, just remember, this is the term which we'll be using. Foreign key is a common column, which helps you to connect to a different table.
100xEngineers: There is one more way to define the relationship.
100xEngineers: is… How many users can send how many messages? Can one user send one message, or only one message?
100xEngineers: No, right? In this case, we described one user can send multiple messages, but the opposite is not true. One message cannot contain more than two users as their user ID, or as their user who has generated this message. So that is not true.
100xEngineers: This description of defining the relationship is… one too many.
100xEngineers: Is known as the relationship for this But…
100xEngineers: This is how we define the relationship between entities. So right now, I'll say my… one user.
100xEngineers: Is related to many messages, which means one user can have many messages, but Messages cannot have multiple users.
100xEngineers: That will be only one. So, this is why it is one-to-many. One user.
100xEngineers: 2 messages 1 user, 4 messages 1 user, 6 messages.
100xEngineers: That's the ratio, and that's the relationship.
100xEngineers: This is the three things and the three core principles of designing database systems, which is known as entities, attributes, and relationship.
100xEngineers: This is relationships.
100xEngineers: Now, there are more relationships than this. It's not the only one. We'll talk more about it.
100xEngineers: But,
100xEngineers: I hope this is clear. I hope one-to-many is clear. Any confusion in one too many. Any confusion in understanding the relationship, understanding why we need a common column.
100xEngineers: Awesome.
100xEngineers: Yes.
100xEngineers: Okay, let's move to the next part. Let's move to the…
100xEngineers: One more thing to just keep in mind, although I'll explain this when we start building it, that these answers definitely help your direction, but they are not the final shape. This is the first draft. This is the first sketch that you guys are building.
100xEngineers: Over time, you also check these things against the lifecycle, against what you are building as a business, what makes sense for the product, and then you actually build the final shape. So, just to tell all of you that
100xEngineers: this is a starting point, not the end state. So it's okay even if we miss some entities, some attributes, we are right now in the draft stage.
100xEngineers: I think we discussed this exercise already.
100xEngineers: So I'll move to the… we discuss, okay, it could be user, it could be conversation, it could be messages,
100xEngineers: are a user, each chat session is a conversation. One thing which we have not discussed as here, so this is what I discussed with my dear friend, Claude.
100xEngineers: And Claude has told me there could be multiple entities, so this is what Claude's answer is. It has said, user and message is something which we identified, but along with that, conversation and plan.
100xEngineers: although I can argue that Plan could be a type of message, but
100xEngineers: A generated plan in future can also be linked to a product, or maybe something more complicated, because plan
100xEngineers: Can be a starting point to a full-fledged product.
100xEngineers: If you think about it, the MVP plan which you guys have built.
100xEngineers: for the next 21 days, and for the assignment number 1, it starts with a text document. But essentially, it also helps you to do and conduct user interviews.
100xEngineers: if you document those things, that would maybe become like a spreadsheet. It can help you to, like, make sense of your, the entire hypothesis, which could be a whole document. It could also help you to define what you want to build, maybe present a deck and a demo. So, over time.
100xEngineers: This is specifically for our use case, and I'm trying to give you the reason that if we tomorrow scale this application, because yesterday, the ArabsApp example only does
100xEngineers: this plan step, but tomorrow, let's say if I want to do this thing, and Arav completes this plan, and he wants to share that, hey, after doing this plan, for step number one, I created the
100xEngineers: I would say, like, one project. This is the Excel sheet where I stored the data. For step number two, I created a presentation. This is a deck. For step number three, I created a codebase. For step number four, I created the NHN workflow.
100xEngineers: this plan can actually grow more than a message. Then it needs a whole entity itself, because then it is describing
100xEngineers: different parts of it. If somebody's still confused about this plan because it's a part of my discovery process, I'll just quickly walk you through what I meant when I said this.
100xEngineers: If you remember the MV plan, this is a plan which
100xEngineers: out of, like, hopefully get, and will I… we'll basically work with him, in the same manner, that first day he'll take some,
100xEngineers: like, interviews, and then… then do a diagnosis call, and then do the workflow ranking, and then, like, create some assignments, talk to… talk about it,
100xEngineers: All of these can also have their own assets and own, I would say the…
100xEngineers: attributes, maybe this… this part of workflow ranking, maybe this part of doing the intake and screening with screening questions can have, like, multiple other students, and in order for us
100xEngineers: for me to make sense, I need to see, like, how many people I have spoken to, what are the questions which I asked, or what Arav has asked, right? Did they actually pay? So, now I need something which is more than just a text.
100xEngineers: And that is a point where this can become a different entity altogether. Did you see this? This is how things get…
100xEngineers: evolved over time. And, if you have designed a data system correctly, it's also easier because maybe initially this is just a plan, but you can define one more entity here, and now this becomes, like, a part of our whole system.
100xEngineers: So…
100xEngineers: And then you have plan, your, what are things that plan contains, those are things. But just to give you that, these are a couple of examples of entities which Claude has suggested, and I think I agree with most of them.
100xEngineers: The second thing is, how do you know it is really an entity? Now, this is a test. There are, like, multiple of these tests. One test is…
100xEngineers: I think, Sagar, you will get clarity here, and Yasha as well, and anyone who is, facing this problem, that if you're still confused about entities, you can run this CURD test.
100xEngineers: You learned about create, read, update, delete in the last lecture, the API session, we discussed this.
100xEngineers: If you run it through, can Arav create a single message? Can Arav read the message? Can Arav edit the message? Can Arav delete the message?
100xEngineers: If it can do all of these things within our application.
100xEngineers: I'm not talking about, like, if he can do in his life, in his life, he can do anything what he wants, but can he do all of these things on our application?
100xEngineers: Can he edit these messages? Can he delete these messages?
100xEngineers: Maybe right now we have not built that functionality yet, but…
100xEngineers: definitely, when Arav is writing a message, he's creating it. So he definitely needs, or you can say he has the action to
100xEngineers: delete it as well, update it, edit it. When you use ChatGPT, you have the same thing, right? You can delete it, add it, delete the conversation, edit it. So…
100xEngineers: This also gives you a quick test that if you are trying to, like, find something which, and you're confused, let's say, give a better example, again, picking the tone, the first example which we had, this is the message tone, versus…
100xEngineers: the message itself.
100xEngineers: Now, can we run this test, the correct test, on these two things?
100xEngineers: RF can definitely create a message. RF can definitely read the message, RF can definitely update it, RF can definitely delete it. And this… all of this can exist independently, without touching anything else.
100xEngineers: But can Arav just create a tone?
100xEngineers: without using anything else. Can RF just read the tone without using anything else on our app? Can RF just update the tone without using or affecting anything else in our system? Can RF delete the tone without affecting anything else on our system?
100xEngineers: I would argue that He can't delete the tone.
100xEngineers: Without affecting anything else, because when he delete that tone, what does that tone mean?
100xEngineers: It… the tone has to be associated with something.
100xEngineers: You can't just delete the tone, and you… like, for example, in this case, like, if I just delete the tone, what does that mean for me? I can't delete this table.
100xEngineers: From my database, as a user. Not as a developer, not as a person who's designing it, but as a user, I definitely cannot delete this thing. And you should not allow people to delete
100xEngineers: columns from your database, because then anyone can delete all these columns. So…
100xEngineers: this is one of the tests. Not the… not the most perfect test. I would say this is one of the tests. You'll learn more of these tests as you, like, start doing
100xEngineers: the exercises more. But this is one of the tests.
100xEngineers: But if I… if I ask from the user perspective, Let's talk about message.
100xEngineers: Let's take a look here.
100xEngineers: RM has created, let's say, 2 messages, like, one or two.
100xEngineers: Out of…
100xEngineers: already performed one operation, which is the creation of this message. Now, you can argue that Arav can also create the tone, but I would say tone can only be created after the message is written, or while the message is writing, but after that message is written and stored, only then we'll store the tone. Maybe we'll use LM for that to understand the tone, or maybe we'll use Arab's, like, overall personality to guess the tone.
100xEngineers: But, every message can have a different tone. Maybe Araf can use
100xEngineers: A formal tone in this message, a casual tone in this message.
100xEngineers: It's basically on Arab, right? Whatever he's writing. So… but the tone itself…
100xEngineers: in isolation doesn't exist, which means, like, tone doesn't need, like, even if I store, like, a table, and we can do this part, let's say if I store the tone.
100xEngineers: And I would say tone of the message.
100xEngineers: First of all, tone of message itself violates that.
100xEngineers: Like, it's not a clear, entity, because it's dependent on things. If I just store tone, I need to now define something about it. And the only thing which I can define is the message.
100xEngineers: And then all the things which I'll define here is about the message.
100xEngineers: Because when somebody has created a tone, that's the same time when they've created the message. So we'll see a lot of repetitive values here. This is another test, which you can see. And and that's something which helps, like, over time.
100xEngineers: Now, I'll ask you, Test, do you think the conversation, which is a new entity that we have not built yet.
100xEngineers: So, apart from these two, definitely we know entities are users and messages, and a plan as well, but…
100xEngineers: There is one entity, which Claude suggested, it's called conversation.
100xEngineers: Let's test whether… Conversation is actually an entity or not.
100xEngineers: Auro opens the app on Monday.
100xEngineers: Creates a chat. On Tuesday, he opens it again.
100xEngineers: A fresh conversation.
100xEngineers: Each can be started, reopened, deleted.
100xEngineers: Can you perform the CRUD test here?
100xEngineers: Can Arav create a new conversation?
100xEngineers: Can I open it, which means read it.
100xEngineers: Updated, deleted. Yes.
100xEngineers: it passes that test. That also gives a slight intuition. So this is an intuitive test, I'm sharing, like.
100xEngineers: These, again, not as the absolute, exercise or test to judge it, but these things help.
100xEngineers: But as of now, conversation is passing the test. So again, this is… we are in the draft stage.
100xEngineers: I would, like…
100xEngineers: get it right, and this is the exactly correct answer. We can create, reopen, and delete a conversation on its own, and conversation can exist on its own because
100xEngineers: RF can create multiple of them, right? And, multiple conversations can have multiple messages in itself.
100xEngineers: Second quick question.
100xEngineers: to test our grid operation theory.
100xEngineers: Is email address an entity?
100xEngineers: Arav signs up with an email address like aravatmail.com.
100xEngineers: What is the answer here? What do you think? First of all, can we do the Curt test here?
100xEngineers: In a way, we can do that test, right? Like, we have already the email field Here.
100xEngineers: But do you think RF can create email on our application?
100xEngineers: Like, this specific email. We don't have, first of all, functionality to create any emails.
100xEngineers: RF can only write email in the email field, if you ask him.
100xEngineers: He cannot create a new f-
100xEngineers: email from scratch, or delete email from scratch, because we are not building an email software. But actually, email is an entity for Gmail.
100xEngineers: And that's why the business context is the primary…
100xEngineers: way to look at entities and these attributes, because
100xEngineers: in our application, email doesn't need a whole table itself, because something which we are not creating, our users are not creating, they are just, like, passing it. And in isolation, can email exist, and we can make sense of it? If I just create a table of email here.
100xEngineers: And I'll write a bunch of email IDs. And, first of all, the attributes will be, let's say, ID or the…
100xEngineers: Email ID.
100xEngineers: And I'll add a bunch of email IDs here. Will this thing tell me anything? Maybe we can have user IDs as well, but will this tell me anything?
100xEngineers: Because it will only tell me that this user has this email, and I can get the same information from user table, that Arav has this email. So this table in itself doesn't justify the existence of it.
100xEngineers: That is another test which it failed.
100xEngineers: And definitely, we can't create a new email on the platform, so it failed the correct test as well.
100xEngineers: It only describes a user. If it only describes a user, then it is… It is an attribute.
100xEngineers: It just describes the user right now. But if you are building an email client, if you are building something like Gmail, or SuperHuman, which is an AI-asserted email client, then email would be an entity.
100xEngineers: So there is a nuance to it. This is confusing. Database design.
100xEngineers: is something which is tricky, and that's why we are trying to spend some time here. But I hope you get the context of our application. No, I don't want to confuse you that it could be your entity somewhere else. Let's come back to it. Our example. We'll stick to what we are building for RF.
100xEngineers: Last question on this topic. Is message an entity?
100xEngineers: I think this is a pretty easy one, because all of you have seen this part.
100xEngineers: message is entity, and you can do all the same tests which we have done with email, and you'll see that it passes all those things. I'll not repeat it, because they've already done it.
100xEngineers: Now, let's do the same test with attributes. Attributes are what an entity carries. They become the columns of its table. We have seen all of this thing right now.
100xEngineers: We can take one message in our chat. What are 3 facts would you need to recreate this?
100xEngineers: role, content, created at. So, something which we have discussed already. One thing which is, interesting here is that
100xEngineers: You can describe the entire… Entity with these attributes.
100xEngineers: The more detailed description you have, The more,
100xEngineers: I would say the information you can capture and the more things you can infer. At the end of the day, it's all about data, right? So, the thing here with about attributes is that whenever you're designing any kind of entity in your database, let's say when you're building the message, initially, it's just like.
100xEngineers: maybe a content and a role, and create that. But over time, your app will see, reasons to add more things, because you want to capture more data, you want to understand, maybe if RF…
100xEngineers: like this message. If Arav disliked this message.
100xEngineers: If you look at a very good exercise here, if you look at ChatGPT, and you can, like, reverse engineer that what kind of things ChatGPT
100xEngineers: Uses in the message.
100xEngineers: So it's…
100xEngineers: On a surface of it, it looks like a simple, plain text message, but if you see right now, if I highlight on this message, I can copy the message. I can edit this message.
100xEngineers: And on the output side, I can click on this share icon, and I can share this specific conversation message. I can try again with this particular message, but with a different model. I can branch a new conversation from this message.
100xEngineers: I can read this message out loud.
100xEngineers: With just one message, you can see how many actions we can perform.
100xEngineers: All of this is because ChatGPT is storing the information.
100xEngineers: So that it understands
100xEngineers: these are the things which we can do. On a surface, it might look like something similar to what we are building for ARP, that, hey, message content, ID, timestamp, maybe a role.
100xEngineers: good enough.
100xEngineers: But the more you go deeper, and you can also, like, check the OpenAI's API, what are the attributes they are sending for each and every message, and you can get to see that what exactly are things they are storing. They won't share all the attributes from the actual database, but you still get to see a lot of things which they are using to display this message on your client machine.
100xEngineers: But a good exercise is to keep this in mind, that these attributes are something which
100xEngineers: describes your application over time, it helps you to, like, I would say.
100xEngineers: Capture more and more meaning, and map more and more reality to things.
100xEngineers: One other way to look at attributes is the colors and the definition, right?
100xEngineers: You have videos in… Low quality resolution?
100xEngineers: maybe black and white videos you can have, or maybe pictures which are, like, 8-bit images, if you have seen those images, I don't know, like, how many of you are, 8-bit…
100xEngineers: There used to be a time when we used to play these games.
100xEngineers: the 8-bit retro games, the Mario and, so-called these. The reason why we call is 8-bit is because this is…
100xEngineers: Represented and built with 8 bits of pixels.
100xEngineers: Like, the per-per things, and that's why it looks sort of pixelated sometimes, right? It's not the most high-definition things. As compared to now, you have, like, something like GTA, right? And which has, like, very high definition, which has multiple bits. So, what is the difference between Mario and GTA? Or maybe Mario versus, like, any other high-definition game which you play right now on a mobile?
100xEngineers: is the amount of attributes which Mario is using to Display the information to you.
100xEngineers: why I'm telling you all of this is because it also directly impacts the amount of data you are storing, also determines the amount of
100xEngineers: Information you will be sending and receiving back.
100xEngineers: which results into the speed of data. If I want to optimize for lowest file size.
100xEngineers: I want to optimize for the fastest speed.
100xEngineers: lowest latency, which means the messages need to be faster, the information needs to be as fast as possible, the amount of storage should be as low as possible. I need to reduce the attributes.
100xEngineers: this is one of the optimization techniques which is done by some of the professional data scientists and engineers. It's called dimensionality reduction. So, it's a term in machine learning as well. Slightly extra information, not needed for our conversation, but
100xEngineers: it's really, like, helpful. So, there are, like.
100xEngineers: big data. And, as you see, like, more and more data, and you work with more and more data, you'll realize that
100xEngineers: There are, like, enterprise…
100xEngineers: data system and database system, which captures not only these 5-6 attributes, maybe, like, thousands of attributes about each and every entity. But the problem with thousands of attributes is that it becomes difficult, as you see that, because it needs more storage, each and everything needs storage.
100xEngineers: Each and everything needs time, because the amount of information I have to send back to my client, because all of this information.
100xEngineers: Somebody needs to first tour.
100xEngineers: The more data we have, the more space it will take. The more time it will take, because it needs to go to the front end, and this is gonna be happening on the internet.
100xEngineers: So, which is already, like, a network, right, which… where we are sending data in packets. So, the more data you have, the more time it will take to send back to your user. In the cases of real-time data, in cases where you need, like, something faster.
100xEngineers: One other thing which machine learning engineer data scientists use is they reduce the number of attributes which still describes the data.
100xEngineers: But, without storing all the information.
100xEngineers: Why we are learning all of this is because these things play a very important role, and this becomes the first principle of designing better systems for both deterministic as well as probabilistic software. Applies in computer science, applies in machine learning, applies in data science as well, so…
100xEngineers: Some of you might think that this is a very common topic, something which I'm telling some of you might feel this is easy, but this is… if you multiply this to a larger data system, things get more and more complex.
100xEngineers: So, I'll… Share, like, Nick's example here after this.
100xEngineers: Now, what is the hard part? In this entire exercise, the hardest part is actually drawing the boundary, because
100xEngineers: Defining the attributes and defining the entities is still something which I believe, even if you are a beginner, you can do it right now.
100xEngineers: You don't need to…
100xEngineers: become, like, a data science expert, or, like, do a degree program, or learn different tutorials. I think we really spent, like, a couple of minutes, and we all were able to intuitively get to design the entities and attributes.
100xEngineers: Most of the beginners make mistakes, and even experts, like, I have made, like, very poor designs in past, which has caused me, like, a lot of money. And by the way, like, each and every decision which you make on entities, attributes, and relationships directly also applies to the cost you and your company is bearing. Because the more data you have, the more attributes you have, the more tables you have, you need to pay for more.
100xEngineers: And you need to pay for each and every request. So this is also the optimization and engineering game, which we are, also learning along with this.
100xEngineers: But, the hardest thing, which I want all of you to think about is right now, is that
100xEngineers: Same words can be an attribute in one app, an entity in another app. How do you define the boundary?
100xEngineers: How do you define the boundary? As we discussed, that email can be an entity in an email software, but email is an attribute in our software?
100xEngineers: RM lets the user
100xEngineers: pick a tone for the plan, right? When Arav built a new workflow, or in case, like, here I am building a workflow for Arav, which
100xEngineers: let's say, if I'm picking a tone for the plan.
100xEngineers: We understand that tone is an entity, not the attribute.
100xEngineers: But the question here is, does your answer change if user could save and reuse the name tones?
100xEngineers: Now, I'll create more confusion to… to this, and
100xEngineers: the thing which I just clarified.
100xEngineers: exactly here.
100xEngineers: The tone versus message. And we just did a test here.
100xEngineers: Some people will find it annoying, although.
100xEngineers: But it's okay, you need to bear with me.
100xEngineers: After declaring that tone is an attribute, I asked you a question.
100xEngineers: Does your answer change?
100xEngineers: if…
100xEngineers: A user could save and reuse name tones. We can create the styles, or tone writing styles, and we can have multiple of those things, and user can save it.
100xEngineers: Do you think the nature of…
100xEngineers: What tone is will change or not.
100xEngineers: If the nature will change, do you think then…
100xEngineers: Tone will become an attribute, or will become an entity, or will still be an attribute here.
100xEngineers: Yes.
100xEngineers: Tone will change, and tone will become an entity, because now you can apply the same crut test. If somebody can describe the tone, the tone…
100xEngineers: is the entity, and the tone now has a description. It's a type. The type could be casual, could be formal.
100xEngineers: The tone could be… maybe there could be a template here for tone.
100xEngineers: There could be a template for casual tone, formal tone. There could be, like, multiple other things, and every tone is associated with a message, so it needs a message ID as well.
100xEngineers: now we are defining these things. And a user can create new tones on our system.
100xEngineers: So we can create… RF can create and reuse the existing tones from the past. We can maybe add a settings. In order for us to describe and display this, the thing which I will be needing is, I need to create one settings icon here. So let's say I create one settings icon.
100xEngineers: And somebody who click on setting icon, then I can maybe, like, open a window, and in that window, I'll ask Arif that, hey, you can describe the tone.
100xEngineers: what do you want your tone to be? Maybe I can take another input.
100xEngineers: So here I can ask Arav to describe the input, and Arav can save tone.
100xEngineers: And when I'm doing all of this, I need a different table.
100xEngineers: Because now, same thing, it also might need… might have the timestamp as well.
100xEngineers: So it changes… it changes the nature of the entities and attributes. It is confusing. It is also the difficult part of designing the database system, because you need to understand the domain really well. The reason why I keep
100xEngineers: Explaining and keep reiterating this a lot is why domain expertise is important, and why the exercise number one, which we did in the week one, is more important than anything else we will be doing, is because if you don't have clarity about the domain where you're operating, the domain where you're solving the problem, you cannot describe these things, you cannot understand
100xEngineers: And identify what will be the entity for our application, because This is the…
100xEngineers: information which will help you, to build the entire architecture of your application, and without understanding your users, because if you have, imagine, never spoken to RF,
100xEngineers: If you have never spoken to, like, people like Arav.
100xEngineers: How would you describe that, should we keep tone as an entity or an attribute?
100xEngineers: Maybe Arav and people like Arab need different type of tones. Maybe they need different type of messages because, let's say Arab is using the same application, one for the personal workflows and one for the professional workflows, or maybe one for the different industry, and different industries need different tones. Medical need a medical tone.
100xEngineers: And if we have done the interviews, we have the data, and then we can describe, and we can use that data to design a better database system, which eventually help us to keep everything efficient.
100xEngineers: So the goal is the boundary is decided by the product requirements, not by the word itself. So we need to also understand this. And, let's do a quick check. I think this is the easiest one.
100xEngineers: Don… As of now, based on what we have discussed, let's say we are not writing it.
100xEngineers: Forget about, like, the conversation which we had, like, just a few minutes ago.
100xEngineers: Do you think entities are two? Entity in this context is an attribute, or…
100xEngineers: what I'm saying. I'm saying tone is an entity or attribute.
100xEngineers: If we give the context about Arav's plan.
100xEngineers: is written in chosen tone, formal, casual, tones are not saved and reused anywhere. It's a description, and it's a clarification which we have given. If this is true, then attribute, then tone is the attribute of a plan. But if this is not true, then the tone can become an entity. So.
100xEngineers: Having clarity and mentioning the clarity while designing the database is also important.
100xEngineers: Let's do a quick check. Entity or attribute?
100xEngineers: Attachment. What do you think attachment is?
100xEngineers: Is it a root of all suffering?
100xEngineers: Attachment is the root of all suffering, that's what Buddha said, right?
100xEngineers: This used to be my wallpaper for a very long time.
100xEngineers: But this is not the option which we have, unfortunately. Adjustment is not the root of all suffering.
100xEngineers: In this context. So, what is attachment?
100xEngineers: Entity or attribute.
100xEngineers: RF can upload attachments.
100xEngineers: Which means Araf can upload a screenshot, a document, just like what we can do in ChatGPT. We can upload these attachments
100xEngineers: I can upload these docs, I can upload PDFs.
100xEngineers: a lot of things, let's say if I upload it right now, let's see how ChatGPT handles this, because unfortunately, I don't have…
100xEngineers: It would be,
100xEngineers: This is the document, and it's sending it as part of my message. It's a long document, by the way. So…
100xEngineers: Attachment as an attribute.
100xEngineers: This attribute can be folders and hence docs and PDFs.
100xEngineers: That's the beauty of this exercise. It creates that cognitive dissonance in your head. This can be an entity, and this can be an attribute.
100xEngineers: And that's why this is difficult, and that's why this is also worth a lot.
100xEngineers: Because when you… when you have that skill with you, when you have this…
100xEngineers: Understanding of, like, building these systems and defining the entities and attributes, which model the reality.
100xEngineers: you're kind of becoming an applied philosopher. I teach this to, like… I used to teach this to engineering students, and I tell them that computer science engineers, especially the engineers who are working on data design and data engineers.
100xEngineers: They are applied philosophers, because essentially we both are seeking truths.
100xEngineers: But philosophers just talk about truth, and data engineers implement those truths in machines, and they build something useful out of it.
100xEngineers: So, what we're also trying to see here is that we are trying to see whether these attributes are
100xEngineers: Modeling the true reality of the context and the business that we are trying to build.
100xEngineers: Somebody who's curious about philosophy and engineering, I can give you, like, interesting books to read about.
100xEngineers: I wasted a lot of time, by the way, there.
100xEngineers: RF can upload attachment, so… my answer is it's an own entity.
100xEngineers: And the reason it is its own entity, because you can create, delete an attachment independently. And it can be reused across conversations, so it deserves its own table.
100xEngineers: One more thing I can explain about attachment here is that if I put attachment in the message, which I can do that, like, let's say if I make it an attribute.
100xEngineers: The thing which will get difficult for me is that
100xEngineers: what type of attachment is… let's say if I have some… Like, a sheet dot… dot CSV. And then…
100xEngineers: Then I have slides.
100xEngineers: PPT. And then I… I have maybe…
100xEngineers: docs.docx. Now I have different type of attachment.
100xEngineers: Right? And, I have different type of, now, attachment issues.
100xEngineers: Because I can't describe what is the type of one attachment. So should I do this? That this sheet is of split sheet type?
100xEngineers: Again, not the best thing what we learned.
100xEngineers: So… It itself needs… One more attribute to describe what type of attachment it is.
100xEngineers: And then user can create and delete attachment. So this is also a quick test, which we can see why attachment needs its own entity. One thing which I do a lot is when I design these systems, I try to map everything on sheets, and then I see if I can describe everything from here.
100xEngineers: if I cannot, then it becomes very intuitive that, yes, this attribute needs its own table, so I need one more table, an attachment, and now I can write, okay, what is the type of this attachment? I can maybe write the, other things, the size of this attachment, because size is also important, and
100xEngineers: The type is important, how much space it will take, because if it is in, like, a large file, then I might need to store it, and maybe store it in a different place, which will not cost me the same thing.
100xEngineers: And all of these things are important about attachment. So, now this is a good way to also see, like, why it is an entity.
100xEngineers: The last part of this, which is the connection bits. Connections are the whole points.
100xEngineers: That's the whole point of this cohort which we are doing, right? We will be connecting a lot of these dots, and I hope some of you can see the dots right now connecting in front of you. That's the most beautiful thing, that's what Steve Jobs said, right? You can't connect the dots looking forward, you can only connect the dots by experiencing and collecting them and then looking it backward.
100xEngineers: I completely agree with that. A spreadsheet stores facts about one thing. A database stores facts and how things are linked. One thing which is very…
100xEngineers: poorly described in these sheets is how it is related. And I said, we can mention that, hey, we have a user ID which is a common column in the message and in the user table, but it's difficult to only, I would say, describe it in such a way, because
100xEngineers: what is the relationship type? Is it many-to-many, one-to-many? Is it one-to-one? Like, only one message can be sent by one user? Those things are not easy to…
100xEngineers: put in here, and only once I see the database and the content of the database, then I can make the… the, I would say.
100xEngineers: judgment at what type of this relationship, one-to-many or many-to-many, which in reality becomes difficult when you have, like, hundreds of tables and hundreds of attributes. You can't just look at the content and always guess it. So, it… this is exactly where the spreadsheets doesn't help a lot, and we need a more…
100xEngineers: complicated system. I would say this is where we need the feature of describing the relationship, and that is the exact same thing which
100xEngineers: is solved by… This thing called relational… database.
100xEngineers: System.
100xEngineers: A relational database is a system that stores organized data in structured tables consisting of rows and columns, and tables are linked to one another using common data points. These are keys. In our case, the key which is common, we call it foreign key, making it efficiently to query relationships and maintain the strict data entity.
100xEngineers: It's a fancy file system.
100xEngineers: But it's the most important one, which you'll be using in this entire journey.
100xEngineers: I hope now some of you will get that why we need relational database, not just any database. There are different types of database, by the way, we'll learn more about it as we start implementing it. But as of now, if we are building an application, and that application has a shape, what we did in this entire last
100xEngineers: 2 hours. I actually, like, just saw the time.
100xEngineers: Time has, I think, blew while I was, like, to explain all of this, but…
100xEngineers: What we have done in the last 2 hours is that we just described the shape of the data. When we started the session, we just had the idea of what is the input and what is the output and how it processed. But what we did this entire session is we had described the shape of this data.
100xEngineers: And this shape of the data tells us that we need entities, like users, messages, which are related to each other in one-to-many relationship.
100xEngineers: And now we have a clear first principle reasoning that why we need a relational database, because we need to map these relationships. We can't use just different files, and maybe we can't use just any database which doesn't have any structure. This is how you reason, this is how you get that reasoning.
100xEngineers: Why you need a particular solution.
100xEngineers: It also becomes a very core part of the decision-making frameworks, which I'll be sharing with all of you in the upcoming weeks, at how to decide which database is better for your needs. This is the first principle for that. You need to model your entities, attributes and relationship. It answers million-dollar questions to a lot of companies. If you go to any big tech, any enterprise right now, the million-dollar question for each of them is.
100xEngineers: what kind of database do you want to use for which data shape, or which data set you have, because it can change the cost completely. Somebody can use and implement simple files, but the read and write for those files, if it is related in a very complicated manner, can increase very fast, and it will reduce the overall
100xEngineers: Experience, maybe increase the time as well.
100xEngineers: If you use something which is very complicated for a system which doesn't need all this relationship, let's say if you only have users as one entity, and you end up implementing the most fancy and expensive vector database for it, doesn't make sense, you're just overpaying for something which you don't even need.
100xEngineers: So, having this understanding of what kind of database you need for your problem statement is something which is very important, and I hope you got. For this problem statement, for Arav, I'm gonna use relational database. In relational database, we have multiple options. The most common database, we have something called SQL database.
100xEngineers: In this, this is the Postgres SQL.
100xEngineers: Which is the same database, by the way, that is used by
100xEngineers: OpenAI. So, I think OpenAI had this very interesting article
100xEngineers: Yes, I would recommend all of you to read this. If somebody wants to go. This is a slight, I would say, stretch for this lecture, but if you want to understand, like.
100xEngineers: how OpenAI used a same database that we're gonna use in this program, and how they used it to scale to 800 million. Almost right now, they are touching trillion users with ChatGPT.
100xEngineers: this is the same thing which we're gonna use here. So, there are multiple types of databases. As I said, like, we're gonna use one of them.
100xEngineers: And I, I, hopefully you got the…
100xEngineers: gist of it, why we need a relational one. This is the type of relational one, and one of the most popular relational database out there available, which is open source, as well as free, of course, if you can download it on your server, host it, you don't need to pay for it.
100xEngineers: Now, there are different flavors and different versions which people use. We'll talk about it in the upcoming lectures, but
100xEngineers: What I'll do right now, I'll…
100xEngineers: Pause this part here, because this will take some time.
100xEngineers: And I would recommend you
100xEngineers: If you have gotten all the concepts, right, this was the core concept, and this is the last question. Let me actually ask the last question, then I'll wrap this part here. The last question was, we had all the facts which we stored in the sheet.
100xEngineers: RF has users' conversation, messages, and plans.
100xEngineers: how each of them connects with others, which word keeps appearing. So there are different types of relationships, as we discussed. We discussed one-to-many in our example, because we had one user with many messages. There are also one-to-one, and there are many-to-many.
100xEngineers: Essentially, these are the only three types of relationships, and out of which, one-to-one is very rare. Majority of time, you need to just understand whether it's one-to-many or man-to-many.
100xEngineers: every connection, every relationship, you can describe in these three different shapes. And, it's important to understand, like, what kind of relationships you have. And…
100xEngineers: Once you do this, you'll have a full understanding of these core first principles of entities, attributes, and relationship.
100xEngineers: The diagram which you see on my screen, it tells that one user has one billing profile.
100xEngineers: If Arav has the account, let's say if we start billing it, then we need to make sure that it, it is connected to Arav's account.
100xEngineers: This is one other way how we can describe the relationship.
100xEngineers: One conversation, if you are building conversation as an entity, can have multiple messages. So the relationship between conversation and messages becomes one-to-many. I actually skipped the last part, but
100xEngineers: In this case, the relationship has to be one, because one user cannot have multiple billing profiles.
100xEngineers: This is one-to-one. It's rare, that's why I said, like, it's something which you might not find a lot of times, but there are times when you find it. This is a classy example of it. When you're onboarding a user, one user can only have one billing profile, and one billing profile can have, like, one user. Especially in our case, because
100xEngineers: we don't want, like, multiple partners to pay for other things. When you are, again, designing a plan which has, like, enterprises, which has themes in it, then maybe it can change, but if you're doing only one user, a consumer application where a consumer pays for it, this is one-to-one.
100xEngineers: Conversation to messages? Many to many.
100xEngineers: Now, this is an interesting example of many-to-many, which is… because our app is simple, so I can't give you the example of many-to-many here, but let's say if you are designing for 100x Engineer, we have students, all of you are students, and we have different courses.
100xEngineers: let's say 100X has one course, which is the online course, then we do, like, one for offline, maybe, like, one we do for AI for product managers, for engineers, for designers. You guys can enroll in multiple courses.
100xEngineers: Right? So this is one of the classic parts, and one course… in one course, there could be multiple students as well. So…
100xEngineers: This becomes one of the many-to-many kind of relationships where you cannot put a
100xEngineers: I would say, just one student in one course, or, like, one course in one student, because multiple students can opt for multiple courses, and multiple courses can be operated by multiple students. That's the classic way of, like, sharing one of the examples of this. And,
100xEngineers: There are some exercises which…
100xEngineers: I would now recommend you to do, because I just wanted to, like, explain these three examples of entities, attributes, and relationships, and I'll take a pause right now at this point.
100xEngineers: what I will do is, I'll create this entire interactive session as an practice set, although I wanted you to, like, participate in it, but I think we did it live right now, so…
100xEngineers: It's,
100xEngineers: it's gonna be a part of your practice set for this week. What we will be doing is, in the next officer, which you will be attending for the next week, we will take this practice set.
100xEngineers: And at least now you have the principles with you, you understand the three core parts, the things which we use to shape the data. You can answer these questions. There are a couple of questions which I have asked in these practice sets, until keys.
100xEngineers: I'll ask you also to design the Arabs Blueprint, and you will see that once you unlock those answers. And, there is an arena here. In this arena, you will have 10 different exercises.
100xEngineers: From ranging to beginner to intermediate to advanced levels. Once you call all of this, and once you finish all of this, at the end, it will ask you to build your own
100xEngineers: Domain model, your own schema, with your entities, with your attributes, relationship for the app that you guys are building.
100xEngineers: And that is where we end this entire practice set. So it's gonna be a continuation for this week. If you have any questions, if you have any doubts so far about the things which we discussed, you can let me know in the chat. If you don't have any questions, this is the end of the session, and
100xEngineers: I hope you learned something, I hope you can apply these things, and I'll see you guys in the next office hour. But for the people who have any questions, I'll be… I'll answer the questions, and then we'll wrap up.
100xEngineers: Okay, you have added… actually, that's a good idea, Saga, thanks for rewinding.
100xEngineers: I would urge all of you to also put your questions in the Q&A chat, because it becomes easier for me to
100xEngineers: then…
100xEngineers: Go back to it, let me just… Put this here.
100xEngineers: How are the large binary objects, such as images, videos, and documents typically stored? Are they kept in the same database as application data, or separate storage system? Very good question, slightly advanced question, but I'll try to answer it in a simpler manner. Mayura asked this, and this is a very valid point. We were discussing the attachment.
100xEngineers: when…
100xEngineers: Files can have different file sizes. If you upload a video, if you upload, like, a heavy file, zip file, that is, like, let's say, over 1GB,
100xEngineers: And now you are paying for that storage on behalf of a user, but a user doesn't know, right? They can upload any size, any file size. So you need to understand how much one data store is costing you.
100xEngineers: If you go with the classic Postgres kind of database, which is storing all the structured data because it is doing a lot of things, it has a lot of features, it will charge you more for that data. So we usually keep the large files in a separate storage system.
100xEngineers: So, these are known as LFS, which is Large File Storage Systems,
100xEngineers: there are buckets for us, which is, like, not-so-structured database. What we do is we create a link. So one of the easiest ways to actually store any large-size object is
100xEngineers: upload it in a drive, just think of, like, a drive equivalent. There's a service on Amazon, it's called Amazon S3, which is equivalent of you storing or uploading information on your drive.
100xEngineers: Or any cloud, software. And then you take a link of that drive, and then you basically send it, or maybe, like, put that link in your…
100xEngineers: relational database. So that way, you can still connect and still, like, upload the attachment, but you are not paying for the storage on the…
100xEngineers: relational database.
100xEngineers: Because it is uploaded somewhere else. If you have seen this pattern, it happens when you send any large file over the email. If you've used Gmail recently, or maybe you've been a Gmail user, and if you upload anything which is a larger file size, it automatically uploads these files into your drive, and then share the link, so that it doesn't need to store all the information there.
100xEngineers: So that's something which is a good practice. But yeah, we definitely need to use a separate storage, because we don't, need to use all the same features for the larger file size. That's a smarter strategy as well.
100xEngineers: What's a second way of defining a relationship?
100xEngineers: Can you describe, and maybe, I think I forgot the context here, can you give more context, Saksham?
100xEngineers: I think we defined a relationship with a common attribute, which is the foreign key. So every time you have one attribute that,
100xEngineers: It's common between two tables. We had user ID, which was common in user, as well as in the messages. That is one way of defining the relationship. Second way was to define the relationship of how many
100xEngineers: entities are connected to… how many instances of these entities can connect to? How many instances of other entities? Which means, can my user send more than one message? Then it becomes one-to-many.
100xEngineers: If the vice versa is not true. If vice versa is true, which I was showing you in the example of courses and students, when students can take multiple courses, and multiple courses can have multiple students in them, that is the example of many-to-many. So these are the
100xEngineers: Second way of defining relationships. So we have one-to-one, one-to-many, and many-to-many.
100xEngineers: User ID, username, email, password, marriage, message, context type, role, relationship, slash, dating, cash, okay.
100xEngineers: Accurate to understand for how long to store the data according to its type.
100xEngineers: Can you describe this? Actually, I will ask you to unmute, if you can,
100xEngineers: Say the question out loud, because…
100xEngineers: I think I still didn't get the question.
Sagar Batra: Hey, hi, Sid. Mainly,
Sagar Batra: I, I mean to ask the…
Sagar Batra: way to decide the relational data, is it based on questions like, how longer do I want to keep the data? For example, data, for example, attributes or entities like user data or user name, email, password, you would want to keep them forever.
Sagar Batra: Because it doesn't change, right? Versus… or it's like a marriage, in terms of relationships, like you have mentioned, it's like a marriage, right? Secondly, the type of, let's say, attribute is the message, the context, the type, or the role. Let's say the relationship type happens to be dating.
Sagar Batra: Or… and then comes the data type, let's say, cache data, or or, conversation context.
Sagar Batra: that becomes, let's say, a situation shift. Do you think that's a good way to look at it, or…
Sagar Batra: see, the fundamental thing that… the reason… like, where I'm coming from is the question that I'm asking is, how long do I want to keep the data? And at that same time,
Sagar Batra: how frequently does it change? Is it a good way to think about that, or not really?
100xEngineers: It's a good way to think about it, but it doesn't directly map with the exercise that we are doing. I would say that's the second level of what we are doing. Like, today we are just trying to understand the shape of the data, what we are trying to store. What you are telling me is that
100xEngineers: how you can optimize the storage based on the size and based on the duration, how you want… how long you want to store it. So that is more like an optimization of your existing data store. So it's not the same thing, but you're thinking about the same, I would say.
Sagar Batra: I'm going a level deeper.
100xEngineers: Yeah, on, like, on a second level, which is… and we are discussing the level 1 today, so yeah.
Sagar Batra: Okay, so maybe, let's say, a better way, if I would want to come at level 1, the better way would be, relationship type. I know, for the sake of this conversation, relationship type, right? Monogamy, non-monogamy, or poly, for example. It's one-to-many, one-to-one, or… that's a better way to think about it, or.
100xEngineers: Yeah, that's exactly right, yeah, that's an easier way to map whatever we discussed, like, in terms of relationships, yeah.
Sagar Batra: Oh, perfect, thank you so much.
100xEngineers: Yeah. Awesome.
100xEngineers: Actually, I'll ask Saksham as well, because I think I didn't get Saksham's question, so… Saksham, can you…
100xEngineers: Like, define the question… For everybody?
100xEngineers: If you're still there.
100xEngineers: Meanwhile, I'll answer Mayur's question. Yeah, Mayur, actually, you can…
100xEngineers: Can you unmute your right now?
Mayur Agrawal: Can you hear me now?
100xEngineers: Yes.
Mayur Agrawal: Yeah, hi. First of all, I seriously want to, you know, thank you on behalf of the entire C7 cohort, because your sessions are really amazing, and that's why, you know, you can see, I mean, the number of people are present in your session is totally different.
Mayur Agrawal: Coming back to my topic, so yesterday we, used, FastAPI as a framework, right? So, when we are deciding on framework, so definitely that the framework API is going to talk to your database, right?
Mayur Agrawal: So, do we need to,
Mayur Agrawal: like, select a database based on your framework? If yes, then how do we select that for our API? Sorry, for our app?
100xEngineers: A good, good question, Vese.
100xEngineers: It used to be that case, what you're saying, that if you have started working with one technology to build APIs and to build UI, you have to, look for the databases which can support that technology.
100xEngineers: But right now, it's not, because every popular database system, they have the programming language agnostic APIs. And the reason, again, we go back to the first principle of what API is.
100xEngineers: It's the interface that connects two different systems. Maybe these systems do not talk to each other, and that's why we established a common language was JSON.
100xEngineers: So the thing is, as long as any database can implement REST APIs, which is the most common API version of it, or it provides that API version, you can connect it with your application, as long as you also understand how APIs work, and you can, like, consume those APIs. So this is the only requirement right now. You don't need to depend on, let's say, if you've chosen to work with Python or NA10 or any kind of technology today.
100xEngineers: You don't need to, like, limit your choices of databases that you can work with, because all of these databases have APIs right now, and you can consume those APIs. So that's not the case today. However, just to, like, add a slight flavor to the answer, is that
100xEngineers: We definitely can find
100xEngineers: databases which are optimized for the use case, rather than the technology stack. For example, I was saying that in this case, because Arav's data is connected with multiple other tables, and I can see, like, how it can connect in future as well as multiple tables, so I can see relationships
100xEngineers: in the data points. And because of that, I would be choosing relational database. If this problem statement requires me to just have independent and isolated variables, isolated, let's say, entities, one of the examples I can think of right now, if I have to do is,
100xEngineers: let's say a simple message, right, which doesn't… we are not, like, using this message for any kind of plan generation. It's an anonymous app where people are just, like, talking to each other, maybe… have you seen Omega?
Mayur Agrawal: No.
100xEngineers: Yeah, something like that, right? Where Omega exists, and where the entire point of the app is not to store anything, not to use any kind of identity, any kind of thing. The anonymity is a feature of the application.
100xEngineers: In that case, I don't need all of this information. Maybe I can just use an unstructured database, like a non-relational database, because the only thing which I need to store is the conversation, and that is also temporary. I don't want to store it. So…
100xEngineers: if that is the product which you're building, maybe I can decide a different database provider, and also database system. So, that's a better way of, like, looking at the database system.
Mayur Agrawal: Thank you.
100xEngineers: Awesome, thank you.
100xEngineers: Yeah, Sir asked this question, if the…
100xEngineers: If the CRUD test passes, we need to promote it to an entity.
100xEngineers: Is this the criteria? Can we also refer to an entity as a model?
100xEngineers: We have more entities.
100xEngineers: And attributes, as are discussed, as the data grows, it becomes slow. Okay, I think I might ask you to, like, unmute, Yasir, if you can explain this.
Yasir Rauf: Here's it?
Yasir Rauf: So, my question is, for example.
Yasir Rauf: right now, we discussed, if we pass the test, so we need to become as entity. So, in… I am UDU developer, so I call same as things table and table, we call models like tables, and we have attribute in the… all the fields in there. So, is it same things?
100xEngineers: What do you call model? What is the definition of model, as per your understanding?
Yasir Rauf: Creating a table. Creating a table in the database, basically, is the.
100xEngineers: Then it's a different thing, because creating a table means then you are… you are taking the entire, I would say, schema. In a way, actually, let me think about it, because…
100xEngineers: If you're asking me that whether table in the database is equal to entity, then the answer is yes.
100xEngineers: Because that's what we did in the sheets, right? So, every sheet is a representation of an SQL table, which has some rows and columns. So, every sheet, when we named a sheet message user, those sheets can translate to an SQL database, like a table.
100xEngineers: So, in that way, yes, it is the same thing. But it doesn't, like, directly map right now, because we have not… we have not, like, built the whole schema right now, we've not written the code as of now. So, that's the only difference. But conceptually, it's the same.
Yasir Rauf: I have a question, for example. My main agenda is, so I need to optimize my work, okay? So, is there any way, for example, can… I am… we are using same Postgres database in Urdu, so my… I am facing the… my projects where it becomes slow.
Yasir Rauf: Because a lot of data, a lot of tables, more than, I think, 200 tables are created in the projects. So, we… I am, I need to…
Yasir Rauf: find, for learning path to how do we optimize the tables, how we optimize the projects. Do you share some material, related material for this? So I need to deep go what is the Postgres, how we're working, how what is the standard criteria we need to,
Yasir Rauf: move on.
Yasir Rauf: So, for example, we, just, yesterday we explored graphically a, an AI tool which, which, data represent my, like, I think, neurobrains.
Yasir Rauf: So, we need to, go cloud, read my data, it's read very quickly, use less token, and tell me which, these functions are slow, these functions are things, so…
Yasir Rauf: Can you share something, like, so it's…
100xEngineers: Awesome. First of all, good question. Slightly advanced, but I'll still try to answer it and make sure that people will understand this, because it's something which you guys will also face, what Yasir is facing today as a problem, once you have
100xEngineers: as he said, like, maybe 100, 200, thousands of tables in your database. Database eventually becomes slow, because they are reading and writing, and when you're doing a query, that one query is trying to understand the relationship across hundreds of tables, then they are doing the calculation, and that becomes slow over time, when you have multiple related entities and more attributes for those entities.
100xEngineers: So, the question here is, I'll urge, Yasi, to you to think about
100xEngineers: like, from principle-first approach rather than tool-first approach, because I think the question which you are trying to ask, if I get your intent right, is can I share some tools, some techniques which can help you optimize? But I would rather force you to think about the shape of the data.
100xEngineers: and then start making decisions. Now, how I, like, do it myself, let's say if I would be in your position, is…
100xEngineers: I need to understand my domain model really well.
100xEngineers: can I see that the concept which I was telling you, right, which a lot of machine learning engineers use, dimensionality reduction, which means
100xEngineers: what kind of queries, first of all, I am getting. This is the same principle, first, input-output. What is the input I'm getting for my queries? What is the output each and every query is expected to deliver? And…
Yasir Rauf: Okay.
100xEngineers: What is the minimum number of
100xEngineers: attributes, entities I need in my data system, database. Forget about a database you have right now on your company, just think it about, in isolation, draw this on whiteboard. What is the input for, let's say, rank your queries. You might be receiving a lot of SQL queries, I am hoping, right?
Yasir Rauf: The problem is…
100xEngineers: Can you rank those queries, like, in use case?
Yasir Rauf: Yes.
100xEngineers: You know, most people.
Yasir Rauf: Yeah, problem is, there is no tool right now
Yasir Rauf: basically, in Udu, we use ORM functions, and ORM function behind the SQL query runs. So, when I go to Amazon, select a database, and go to monitor, they tell me query. I don't know which function, which user run this query, and some queries are becoming slow, I know.
Yasir Rauf: So, this is the first, problem I, run as a discovery to MVP. I make a tool.
Yasir Rauf: So, maybe after you're reviewing my assignment, so I need some help, I need to optimize, and making this tool. So, I am, this is my KPI in my office, so I need to resolve this. So, that's why I'm creating a V1 tool, and all the discovery, 21 days, I pass this.
Yasir Rauf: So I hope you will see, and I will get the more… good way.
100xEngineers: Sure, yeah, definitely, I'll share that, but yeah, thanks for sharing it. But just, like, on a closing note, to answer that part.
100xEngineers: I would still urge you to, like, actually look for the solution which can first give you the most number of frequent queries. And I know it might not be easy today because you don't have the tool with you, but there are, like, available, like, libraries within the Postgres itself, which can help you to log all the queries. And if your company is using any kind of analytic software, so they also already log things.
100xEngineers: And I assume your company does have some analytic systems which they use to analyze the incoming requests and outgoing requests. That could be one way. If you have anyone who is working as a data analyst in your team or business analyst, that could be a person you can reach out to and understand that if we have a logging system, if you don't have a logging system, then you might need to build that, because that is one of the most important things which I would recommend.
100xEngineers: But if you have it, the first goal is to look at the incoming request from the user side, what are the top queries we are getting, and if we can rank those queries, and then we go back to the whiteboard, and then we can see, like, what is the minimum number of entities and attributes we need to answer these queries.
100xEngineers: that's a good way to start the process. It becomes a very wide, like, I would say the redesign of
100xEngineers: database and data schema. Something which we have done in our previous businesses is that we start with one set of
100xEngineers: query or one set of use case, let's say, which is the highest bottleneck for me. I'll give you an example of, when we were building the voice-based application, one of the highest, I would say the used
100xEngineers: page on that application was the… the chat, because chat is the place where… and this was a group chat, when somebody's, talking, it's basically, like, when people come, they create a room, and they talk to, like, let's say a host, and let's say Sagar is a host, and he's hosting, like, somebody who is
100xEngineers: Famous or popular, and then…
100xEngineers: In chat, people used to go crazy. They used to just, like, write 100 things, and let's say there's 700 people, or 1,000 people who are active in the chat, they're sending thousands of messages. That's where our app becomes slow. It used to become really slow, because there's thousands of incoming data points which are getting stored in our database system.
100xEngineers: And, now the question for us, as you said, like, okay, this is, like, getting slow, what should we do? The first thing is not just looking for a tool, because yes, I can tell you a tool right now that you use by Spark, use XYZ, use different things, maybe, like, which might work for you, which might not work for you, but…
100xEngineers: tool-based suggestion doesn't help anyone. That's personally what I learned, right? You always need to understand the root cause of the problem, and unless until you do that, having or buying any tool or using any tool will just be a band-aid solution for you, right? It's just like what Indian doctors do. I do, like,
100xEngineers: have this, I would say.
100xEngineers: I wouldn't say, like, a very strong opposition, but I don't like the way how a lot of Indian doctors, especially physicians, diagnose people in India, because they just, like, look at the symptoms and they just write the prescription.
100xEngineers: to be honest, this is how we are used to, like, about, like, a lot of medical advice. I don't know if you had the same experience, Yasir. Like, the place where I come from, I think throughout my childhood, whenever I used to visit a doctor, or anyone from my family used to visit a doctor, they used to just, like, ask me, okay.
100xEngineers: what are the things you're feeling, and I say my symptoms, and then they just write a prescription that these are the medicines you should take, come after 5 days, and then after 5 days, based on the symptoms, either the doctor increase or decrease the dose of my medication.
100xEngineers: And that is actually the most flawed way of, like, telling somebody how to, like, take drugs, because you don't know the internal state of body, you're depending on the self-diagnosis and self-reporting of the user. Sometimes, maybe I don't know, like, the difference between a headache of migraine versus the headache of dehydration, and I just, like, still say the headache.
100xEngineers: I can't use the same medicine which solves migration, or migrate, versus dehydration. And, that's the problem with the current advice, which I'm also, like, trying to tell you, and which is common for
100xEngineers: a lot of people who have the same, I would say, the subconscious,
100xEngineers: Training, because we are… we are trained to seek
100xEngineers: these advices, these band-aid solutions that, hey, I'm facing this problem, I have this symptom, my database is slow, my queries are slow, can you please help me with a tool? Can you please help me with XYZ solution? And the thing is, a lot of people can do that. They will… they'll tell you that use the solution. But I think, in my case.
100xEngineers: both for my, like, health, as well as for my programs, this solution didn't help. I had something which is very personal, again, I'm sharing as a part of, like, something which is, like, unofficial here, because I'm thinking of way less people here. I had very severe gut issues.
100xEngineers: Which I've been facing from the last almost 10 years. No doctor was able to, like, diagnose, first of all, and they're not able to, like, understand. They just keep giving me more antibiotics, sometimes, like, some XYZ probiotics and prebiotics.
100xEngineers: It's, like, almost 10 years, like, I've seen, like, the best gut specialist in India, but not able to figure it out.
100xEngineers: Two years ago, I was building my own medical research agent, and this was one of the problem statements which we had for a client, and I realized that the amount of
100xEngineers: randomized control trial and the research paper out there for gut, they all started with the same principle, that you need to understand the gut microbiome, which is basically understanding the gut diversity, like, what kind of bacteria lives inside your stomach. Unless until you know that about your body, no prebiotics and no solution can solve you, because everybody has a very different gut, bacteria diversity.
100xEngineers: And the moment I understood that as a core principle, I started, like, doing these tests. In India, back in the day, I think 3 years ago, there was, especially Bangalore, there was no other company.
100xEngineers: who was doing these gut microbiome tests, you have to, like, go for, like, very highly specialized labs in certain, like, I would say countries, or maybe certain specific locations, and you should send your samples, and that's how you used to get it. Again, not sure, maybe I could be wrong here about this, but I checked Bangalore 3 years ago, it was not here. Two years ago, there was a company who came, who started doing the gut microbiome test. I did the test.
100xEngineers: I uploaded all the reports.
100xEngineers: to this agent, and this agent was using, like, the LLM like Claude, and tried to understand, okay, what is my gut microbiome diversity, and then started, like, explaining me what is the exact bacteria strain which I'm lacking because of that, which I'm having all these issues. And the moment I saw that, it just immediately clicked in front of me that it's a biology.
100xEngineers: Which I've studied already, and I've been facing these gut issues because I don't have this specific strain in my body. And now the solution is not to take more prebiotics or more medicine, it's just to make sure that this bacteria lives inside my gut, and also
100xEngineers: creates a healthy environment, because in the past, I have taken prebiotics, but the problem is
100xEngineers: it doesn't help your body when you just, like, take something externally, because your body doesn't accept it. You need to cultivate the environment, you need to, like, prepare the body. So there are multiple changes you need to bring in your lifestyle, in yourself, to actually, like, have that specific solution.
100xEngineers: No doctor in the last 10 years in the entire Indian medical history
100xEngineers: told me this. This is what I got from Claude.
100xEngineers: By building an agent, by doing my own research. And that's when I realized that how broken the system is, because it was a very simple first principle insight. If somebody would have done a gut microbiome test on my body, they could have figured out that this is a problem. But instead of that, every other doctor just gave me a prescription. Nothing worked.
100xEngineers: Now, why I told this entire story to you? Because this is exactly, like, how our entire industry works. Like, you go to a consultant, please help me, I am facing a problem, give me a solution, give me a tool. They give you a tool. There are hundreds of courses out there teaching you tools. I'll teach you, like, ChartGBT in 5 minutes, 5 AI tools that will change your life.
100xEngineers: 5 AI tools that will increase your revenue.
100xEngineers: All of them making the same mistake, they don't know who you are.
100xEngineers: They don't know what exactly the problem you're facing. They don't know what is the core route. Do you have that particular bacteria strain, or maybe the particular problem?
100xEngineers: And I think unless and until you do the deep dive of that, you can't actually build a solution or solve the problem. So that's my whole advice to you as well as to everybody. I know it might sound like I'm giving an extra
100xEngineers: GAN and extra knowledge about all of this thing, but it's something which has changed the way how I look at everything in my life after that incident, right? When I… when I had this whole breakthrough about, like, what I could not…
100xEngineers: like, I accepted that, like, I had this, like, a poor gut.
100xEngineers: And I just, like, can't have food. But fortunately, after all of that, I can eat everything right now. And it's not because some doctor helped me, it's because I just understood there's something which is missing, and I've fixed that thing.
100xEngineers: Now, I'm not claiming that I'm a doctor or I'm better than any doctor, but it's just, like, first principles help, understanding the root cause of problems help, and that's the same thing which helped me in building businesses as well, in building solutions. So…
100xEngineers: coming back to your answer, I think… if you go back to the whiteboard today and send me the whole data flow.
100xEngineers: talk to an analyst, it might not be easy, you need to find what are the most frequent queries. Where is the bottleneck? First, the problem which I told you, when we were building our application, the bottleneck was on chat, because there was hundreds of or thousands of users writing the chat message at the same time. It was a live conversation. And we realized that is the bottleneck, and we start fixing those things.
100xEngineers: In your case, what is that particular part in your application? Where the bottleneck is, where people are sending most number of queries, where it is getting exactly slow, which are the slowest query in your entire API calls, or entire database? Somebody needs to do auditing there. There are logs already, there are logging software. Look at those logs, look at those things, try to understand which is the slowest, rank the slowest one in the top.
100xEngineers: and start understanding that why this query is slow, because it must be taking some input, and to process the output, it must need more and more entities, which may be, let's say I'm assuming, spread across multiple tables, and it needs to do join queries across those tables to extract the relevant attributes. And because of those join-ins and connecting those relationships, it's taking more time.
100xEngineers: Or maybe it is also something because it might have, like, a larger file size, which it is sending back, and you might can use, like, a slightly faster storage solution for it. So, I don't know the problem statement right now, that's why I said I can't suggest you a tool right now, but this could be one of the ways how I would recommend, and if you do this exercise, do send me the whole data inflow.
100xEngineers: and the output, maybe then I can help you.
100xEngineers: Awesome, thank you. I think I… I had to stop because I'm trying to give up.
100xEngineers: extra information right now, which is not needed. In which case…
100xEngineers: of a chat app, should we use WebSockets? Not relevant to the conversation, but I think I'll discuss this maybe in any other office or a hunch.
100xEngineers: Yes, problem identification is a core skill.
100xEngineers: Cool, awesome. Thank you, guys. I think I'll take a pause here, I have to go. So, thank you so much. I'll see you next week, I'll share the practice set, you guys already have the link.
100xEngineers: So, until then, keep building, and bye-bye, good night.